好的。
Alright.
今天的基本主题是，
The sort of underlying topic for today is
获得良好的多核性能，
really getting multi-core, getting good multi-core performance,
在多核硬件上获得良好的性能，
getting good performance on multi-core hardware,
这是一个非常有趣和令人着迷的话题，
and that's actually very interesting and deep fascinating topic,
有很多不同的有趣的方面。
with many many different interesting aspects.
今天，我们会讨论一小部分，
Today, we're just gonna bite off a fairly small piece,
这就是如何在内核中获得良好的共享数据性能，
and that's how to get a good performance for shared data in the kernel,
读的次数比写的次数多得多。
that's read much more often than it's written.
有很多种具体的案例，
And it turns out there's many kinds of specific cases,
获得良好的多核性能的不同想法是有用的。
in which different ideas for getting good multi-core performance are useful.
我们今天要看的是 Linux 的 RCU ，
We're gonna look at today is Linux's RCU,
它是非常成功的，
which has been very successful,
对于读取繁重的内核数据。
for sort of read heavy data, read heavy kernel data.
这里的一般背景是，
The general sort of background here is that,
如果你有现代机器，
if you have modern machines
有 4 8 16 或 64 核或任意多核，
with four eight or sixteen or 64 or however many cores,
并行运行并共享内存，
running in parallel and sharing memory,
内核实际上是一个并行进程，
the the kernel is really a parallel process, it's a parallel program,
如果你想要有好的性能，
and if you're going to get good performance,
你需要确保内核可以运行大量工作，
you need to make sure that the kernel can run a lot of its work
在不同的内核上尽可能多地并行运行，
as much as possible in parallel on different cores,
为了得到更多，
in order to get that much more,
如果你在八个内核上并行运行内核，
if you can run the kernel parallel on eight cores,
它们都在做有用的工作，
all of them doing useful work,
你可以获得 8 倍的性能，
you can get eight times the performance,
与内核只运行一个内核相比。
than if the kernel could only run a single core.
在高级别上，这显然是可能的，
And, at a high level, this should clearly be possible,
如果你的计算机上运行许多进程，
if you have lots and lots of processes running on your computer,
首先，进程在内核中运行，
the, first of all, the processes are running and executing in the kernel,
我们就没什么好担心的了，
then we have very little to worry about,
它们很可能是并行运行的，
they're likely to run in parallel
而不需要内核做任何事情，
without any kernel having to do anything,
如果你正在运行多个应用程序，
if the processes if you have many applications running,
而且它们很多时候都在进行系统调用，
and they're all making system calls a lot of the time,
不同进程进行的不同系统调用
different system calls made by different processes
似乎应该是独立的，
just seem like they ought to be independent,
而且应该能够在许多情况下继续进行，
and should be able to proceed in many cases,
尽管不是所有情况，
though certainly not all,
但应该能够完全不受干扰地进行，
but should be able to proceed completely without interference,
比如，如果两个进程是 fork 的，
like if two processes are forking,
或者两个进程正在读取不同的管道，
or two processes are reading different pipes
或者读或写不同的文件，
or you know reading or writing different files,
它们没有明显的理由要相互干扰，
there's no obvious reason why they should interfere with each other,
为什么它们不能以总吞吐量的 n 倍并行执行。
why they shouldn't be able to execute in parallel at n times the total throughput.
但是问题是，内核有很多共享资源，
But the problem is the kernel has a lot of shared resources,
为了，出于其他好的原因，
in order to, you know for other good reasons,
内核共享了大量资源，
the kernel shares a lot of resources,
比如内存、 CPU 、磁盘缓存和 inode 缓存，
like memory and CPU and disk cache and inode cache,
所有这些在不同进程之间共享的内容，
and all this other stuff that's actually under the hood shared between different processes,
这意味着即使两个处理器进行系统调用，
and that means that even if two processors are doing system calls,
两个完全没有听说过对方的进程，
two processes that have totally never heard of each other
并且不会交互进行系统调用，
and aren't trying to interact make system calls,
如果那些系统调用碰巧分配内存或使用磁盘缓存，
if those system calls happen to allocate memory or use disk cache,
更多涉及调度决策，
more involve scheduling decisions,
它们很可能最终都使用内核中的数据结构，
they may well end up both using data structures in the kernel,
因此，我们需要一些故事
and therefore we need some story
来说明它们应该如何使用相同的数据，
for how they're both supposed to use the same data
不会相互干扰，
without getting underfoot, without interfering with each other,
多年来，我们付出了巨大的努力，
and there's been enormous effort over the years,
让所有这些案例和内核都运行得很快。
and making kernels, making all these cases and kernels run fast.
我们已经看到了一个以正确为导向的，也就是自旋锁，
We've seen one of course that's oriented towards correctness namely spin locks,
自旋锁是直截了当的，
spin locks are straightforward,
因为这样的事情很容易推理，
as such things go and easy to reason about,
但你知道旋转锁的作用是阻止执行，
but you know what spin lock does is prevent execution,
它的作用是阻止并行性，
it prevents, its job is to prevent parallelism,
在两个进程之间可能存在问题的情况下，
in cases where there might be a problem between two processes,
所以自旋锁直接会降低性能，
so spin locks are just directly away to decrease performance,
这就是它们所做的。
that's all they do.
当然，它们使得推理正确变得很容易，
Of course, they make it easy to reason about correctness,
但它们绝对会阻止并行执行，
but they absolutely prevent parallel execution,
这并不总是那么可取的。
and you know that's not always that desirable.
好的，我们把重点放在读取为主的数据上，
Okay, so again we're going to focus on read heavy data,
在这种情况下，
on the case in which
你的数据主要是读取的，而写入相对较少。
your data that's mostly read and relatively rarely written.
主要使用的例子是链表，单链表，
And the main example in use is a linked list, a singly linked list,
所以你可以想出一个标准的链表，
and so you can think of just a standard link to,
这张图，
this diagram,
有某个全局变量，它是头指针，
there's some sort of maybe global variable, that's a pointer, head pointer,
有一个指针，有一堆列表元素，
just a pointer and there's a bunch of list elements,
每个列表元素都有一些数据，
and each list element has some data
假设它是一个字符串，
and I'll just say it's a string,
比如， hello 这种数据在这个元素中，
like you know "hello" is this sort of data in this element,
并且每个元素还有下一个指针，
and each element also has a next pointer,
指向下一个列表元素，
that points the next list element,
最后有一个指向零的指针来标记结束，
and then finally there's a pointer that points to zero to mark the end,
非常直截了当。
very straightforward.
我们再次假设，
And again we're gonna assume that,
我们感兴趣的这个列表的大部分只是读取，
most uses of this list that we're interested in are just reads,
内核线程或其他什么东西使用这个列表，
you know the the kernel thread or whatever it is that's using this list,
只是在扫描列表，寻找一些东西，
is just scanning the list looking for something,
而不是试着修改列表。
not trying to modify the list.
偶尔也会有写者，
And occasional writers though,
如果没有写者的话，
you know all if there were zero writers ever,
我们完全不需要担心这件事，
we wouldn't need to have to worry about this at all,
因为那将是一个完全静态的永远不会改变的列表，
because it'll be a completely static list, never changes,
我们可以自由读取，
we can read it freely,
但是我们会想象一下，
but we're going to imagine that,
每隔一段时间，
every once in a while,
有人想要写入列表。
somebody comes along and wants to write the list.
这可能意味着，
So that may mean that,
某个其他线程想要修改保存在列表元素中的数据，
some other thread wants to change the data stored in a list element,
或者可能删除一个元素，
or maybe delete an element,
或者可能在某个地方插入一个新元素。
or maybe insert a new element somewhere.
所以即使这样，我们的目标是读取为主，
So even though, it's we're aiming at a mostly reads,
我们也要担心写入的问题，
we do have to worry about writes,
我们需要在面对写入时确保读取的安全。
we need to make the reads safe in the face of writes.
当然，在 xv6 中，
Of course, in xv6,
我们只有一个锁来保护这个列表。
we just have a lock protecting this list,
读者，不仅是写者，
and a reader, that you know not only would writers,
在 xv6 中，不仅写者必须获取锁，
in xv6, not only would writers have to acquire the lock,
而且写者也必须获取锁，
but readers would have to acquire the lock too,
因为我们要排除这种情况，
because we're going to rule out the situation,
在我们读取时，有人在修改列表，
in which while we're reading somebody's actually modifying the list,
因为这可能会使读者看到部分更新的值，
because that could cause sort of the reader to see half updated value
或者跟随无效的指针或其他什么。
or follow an invalid pointer or something.
所以，在 xv6 中，我们有锁，
So in xv6 we have locks,
但是，这有一个缺陷，
but, that has a defect,
如果常见的情况下没有写者，
that if the common cases there's no writers,
这意味着每次有人来读取时，
it means that every time somebody comes along and reads,
在 xv6 中，它们抢占独占的， xv6 自旋锁是独占的，
in xv6, they grab an exclusive, like xv6 spin locks are exclusive,
即使你有两个读者，
even if you have just two readers,
一次也只有一个可以继续，
only one of them can proceed at a time,
所以我们想要的，
so what we'd like,
某种程度上是改善这种情况的一种方式，
sort of one way to improve this situation,
就是有一种新的锁，
would be to have a new kind of lock,
允许多个读者，但只允许一个写者。
that allows multiple readers, but only one writer.
所以我接下来要探索这些，
So I explore those next,
因为它们都很有趣，
actually both because they're interesting,
因为它们帮助激发了对 RCU 的需求，
because they they help motivate the need for RCU,
我们一会儿再谈。
we'll talk about in a little while.
所以这个概念叫做读写锁，
So there's, this notion called read write locks,
它的接口比我们使用的自旋锁的要复杂一些，
and the interface is a little more complicated than the spin locks we're used to,
我们假设有一组调用，
we're going to imagine that there's one set of call,
如果你只想读取什么，
that you call if you just want to read something,
所以我们将想象有一个 r_lock 调用，并传递一个锁，
so we're gonna imagine r_lock call and pass a lock
然后还有一个 r_unlock 调用，
and then also an r_unlock call,
读者调用这些。
and readers call these.
然后有一个 w_lock 调用和 w_unlock 调用，
And then there's a w_lock call and a w_unlock call,
它的语义是，
and the semantics are that
你可以让多个读者获取用于读取的锁，
you can either have multiple readers acquire the lock for reading,
这样我们就会得到并行性，
so we do then would get parallelism,
或者你可以有一个写者获取锁，
or you can have exactly one writer have acquired the lock,
但你永远不能混在一起，
but you can never have a mix,
你永远不能，
you can never have be in,
锁排除了这种可能，
the locks rule out the possible,
读写锁排除了这种可能，
read, read write locks rule out the possibility
有人锁定写入锁并同时进行读取，
of somebody having locked the lock for writing and also reading at the same time,
要么是一个写者，要么是多个读者，没有别的情况。
you're either one writer or lots of readers, but nothing else.
所以这就是。
So that's the.
有一个问题。
A question.
好的。
Yes.
这可能是关于实现细节，
This may be an implementation detail,
但是这个锁方案设置了什么样的机制，
but what kind of mechanisms does this locking scheme put in place
来防止当它们持有读锁时，有人写入。
to prevent someone writing, while they hold a read lock.
没什么，就像 xv6 锁一样。
Nothing, nothing, it's just like xv6 locks, completely.
我们谈论内核代码是由值得信赖的负责任的开发人员编写的，
We're talking about kernel code written by trusted responsible developers
所以，就像 xv6 中的自旋锁一样，
and so just like spin locks in xv6,
如果代码使用锁不正确，那么它就是不正确的，没有。
if the code is using locks incorrect, it's incorrect, there's no.
好的。
Okay.
这就是典型内核的编写方式，
And this is the way you know typical kernels are written,
你需要假设，
you just have to assume that,
开发内核的人遵循他们自己的规则。
people developing the kernel are following their own rules.
好的。
Okay.
好的，再说一遍我们关心的原因是，
Okay, and again the reason why we care is that,
如果我们有一个读取为主的数据结构，
if we have a mostly read mostly data structure,
我们希望有多个读者能够同时使用它，
we'd love to have multiple readers be able to use it at the same time
通过拥有多个内核获得真正的加速。
to get genuine speedup from having multiple cores.
好的，如果这里没有问题，
Alright, so, if there were no problem here,
这就是答案，
this would just be the answer,
我们不需要读今天的论文，
we wouldn't have needed to read today's paper,
但事实证明，
but it turns out that,
如果深入查看发生的细节，
if you dig into the details of what actually happens,
当你使用读写锁时，
when you use read write locks,
特别是对于大量读取的数据，
especially for data that's actually read a lot,
这里有一些问题。
there's some problems.
为了看看发生了什么，
And in order to see what's going on,
我们必须看一下实现。
we actually have to look at the implementation.
Linux 有一个读写锁实现，
Linux indeed has a read/write lock implementation in it,
这是 Linux 代码的一种简化版本。
and this is a kind of simplified version of the Linux code.
这里的想法是有一个 rwlock 结构体，
The idea is that we have a struct rwlock,
就像 xv6 中的 lock 结构体，
which is like struct lock in xv6,
而且它里面有一个计数，
and it has a count in it,
如果计数为 0 ，
if the count is 0,
这意味着锁没有被任何人以任何形式持有，
that means that the lock is not held by anybody in any form,
如果计数为 -1 ，
if the count is -1,
则表示写入者已加锁，
that means that a writer has it locked,
如果计数大于 0 ，
and if the count is greater than 0,
这意味着 n 个读取者已加锁，
that means that n readers have it locked,
我们需要跟踪它们，
and we need to keep track of them,
因为我们只能让一个写入者进来，
because we can only let a writer in,
如果读取者数量降到 0 的话。
if the number of readers descends to 0.
好的，有人问了关于添加的问题。
Okay, so somebody asked about addings.
不，我不确定聊天里有问题，
No, I'm not sure if there's a question in the chat,
如果有的话，请打断我。
interrupt me if there is.
读锁定函数，它处于循环中，
The read lock function, that's sit in a loop,
因为如果有写者，
because if there's a writer,
我们必须等待写者，
we have to wait for the writer,
它看起来，
it looks,
它获得了当前 n 的值的副本，
it grabs a copy of the current n value,
如果该值小于 0 ，则表示有一个写者，
if this less than 0, that means there's a writer,
我们只需要继续我们的循环，继续旋转，
and we just need to continue our loop, gonna spin,
等着写者离开，
waiting for the writer to go away,
否则，我们想要增加这个值，
otherwise we want to increment that value,
但是我们只想增加它，
but we only want to increment it,
如果它仍然大于或等于 0 ，
if it's still greater than or equal to 0,
所以我们不能，有很多事情我们不能做，
so we can't, there's many things we can't do,
我们不能简单地加 1 ，
we can't, for example, just add one,
使用标准的 n 等于 n 加 1 ，
with standard n equals n plus one,
因为如果写入者偷偷进入，
because if a writer sneaks in,
在我们检查 n 的值和尝试增加它之间，
between when we check the value of n and when we actually try to increment it,
那么我们可能继续，并增加它，
then we may actually go ahead and increment it,
而同时，某个写者把它设为 -1 ，
at the same time, that some writer is setting it to -1,
这是不对的。
which is wrong.
所以，我们需要增加它，
So we need to increment it,
只有它在我们检查之后没有修改过值，
only if it hasn't changed value since we checked it
并验证其大于或等于 0 ，
and verified that is greater than or equal to 0,
人们这样做的方式是，
and the way people do that is,
他们利用特殊的原子指令，
they take advantage of special atomic or interlocked instructions,
这是你在前面看到的，
which you saw before,
用于在 xv6 中实现自旋锁。
for the, for implementation of spin locks in xv6.
而原子性指令，
And the interlocked instruction,
这是一种特别方便的被称为比较和交换的指令，
that's one that's particularly convenient to use as something called compare and swap,
这个想法是比较和交换有三个参数，
the idea is the compare and swap takes three arguments,
我们要执行操作的某个内存位置的地址，
the address of some location of memory that we want to act on,
我们认为它拥有的值，
the value that we think it holds
以及我们希望它拥有的值。
and the value that we'd like it to hold.
比较和交换的语义是，
And the semantics of compare and swap are that,
硬件检查，
the hardware checks,
硬件首先设置内部锁，
the hardware first sort of basically sets an internal lock,
使得在给定内存位置上一次只执行一次比较和交换，
that makes only one compare and swap executed a time on a given memory location,
然后硬件检查这个位置的当前值仍然是 x ，
then the hardware checks that the current value of that location is indeed still x,
如果它仍然是 x ，
and if it still x,
将它设置为第三个参数，它将是 x 加 1 ，
sets it to this third argument, which is going to be x plus one,
然后指令产生 1 ，它的值，
and then the instruction yields one, its value,
如果比较和交换观察到当前值不是 x ，
if compare and swap observes that the current value isn't x,
那么它不会改变那个内存位置的值，
then it doesn't change the value the memory location,
并返回 0 。
and it returns 0.
所以这是一个原子性的，
So this is basically an atomic,
如果位置是 x ，则设置为 x 加 1 。
if the location is x, set to x plus one.
它必须是原子的，
It has to be atomic,
因为有两件事在发生，
because there's really two things going on,
硬件检查当前值，并将其设置为新值。
the hardware is checking the current value and setting it to a new value.
关于比较和交换，有什么问题吗？
Any questions about compare and swap?
我有个问题，
I have a question,
如果有一个读者和 r_lock 需要继续，
if there would be a reader and r_lock needs to continue,
那么 w_unlock 是否会将值重置回 x 。
would w_unlock reset the value back to x.
w_unlock ，如果有一个写者，
Um, w_unlock, if there's a writer,
w_unlock，它会设置 n 为 0 ，
w_unlock, which I'm afraid it shows set n to 0,
因为只能有一个写者。
because there can only be one writer.
而 r_unlock 所做的是，
If there's what r_unlock does is
使用另一个比较并交还来减少 n 。
use another compare and swap to decrement n.
好的，这会发生什么，
Okay, because, what happens,
如果写者锁处于 x 正在计算。
if writer locks lock between when x is being computed and.
在这里吗？
So, right here?
不，在 if 和 x 之间。
No, between the if and x somehow.
好的，我不太明白你问的是什么时间，
Okay, okay, it's, I'm not sure I understand exactly what time you're asking,
但这绝对是个好问题，
but it's absolutely good question,
如果在这个序列中的某个地方调用了 w_lock ，会发生什么。
what happens if w_lock is called somewhere during this sequence.
对我来说，调用 w_lock 最危险的时间是，
And for me the most dangerous time for w_lock to be called is
在检查之后，但在比较和交换之前。
after this check, but before the compare and swap.
那么，我们假设读锁已经完成，
So, let's imagine that read lock has done,
已经看到 x 或 l->n 是 0 。
as far as seeing that x, that x or l->n is 0.
好的，也许我们在这里，
Okay, so maybe we're right, we're right here,
并且 x 等于 0 。
and x is equal to 0.
我们已经检查过了，检查已经完成了，
We've already checked, the check is finished,
然后就在这个时候，在另一个核心上，
and then right at this time on another core,
一些其他线程调用了 w_lock ，
some other thread calls w_lock,
它首先进行比较和交换。
and it actually gets its compare and swap in first.
所以，另一个核心正在尝试获取写锁，
So on the other core is trying to grab the write lock,
比较和交换将查看 l->n 是否为 0 ，
compare and swap is going to see if l->n is 0,
我们假设 n 是 0 ，那么这个测试是真的，
let's assume that n is 0, so this test is true,
并且在另一个核心上的比较和交换
and the compare and swap is on that other core
将设置 n 为 -1 ，
is going to set n to -1,
现在锁加锁了，
now the locks locked,
但是我们在这个代码中仍然认为 n 是 0 ，
but we still think that n is 0 in this code,
即使锁已经锁定了。
even the locks locked.
现在我们要执行，
And now we're gonna execute,
回到读取核心，
back on the reading core,
我们要执行比较和交换，
We're going to execute compare and swap,
但是我们要在这里传递 0 ，
but we're going to pass 0 here right,
这是我们要传递的值，
this is the value we actually,
我们要传递我们看到的值，
we're going to pass in the value we actually looked at,
而不是 n 的当前值。
not the current value of n.
当我们查看它时，它是 0 ，
And when we looked at it,it was zero,
所以我们要在这里传递 0 ，
so we're going to pass 0 here,
我们会告诉比较和交换，
and we'll telling compare and swap,
对它加一，
look only add one to,
只有在当前值为 0 时，将它设置为 1 。
only set it to 1, if its current value is 0.
但在这一点上，它不是 0 ，而是 -1 ，
But it's not 0, at this point, it's -1,
所以这个比较和交换会失败，
and so this compare and swap fails,
不会修改 n ，并返回 0 ，
does not modify n, returns 0,
这意味着我们将回到这个循环的顶部，然后重试，
and so that means we'll go back to the top of this loop and try again,
当然现在 n 是 -1 。
of course now n is -1.
这可能和前面的问题有点关系，
This may be related to the previous question a bit,
但是，是否会发生中断，
but, is it possible for an interrupt to occur,
当在 CAS 参数中计算 x 加 1 时？
when that x plus 1 is being computed in the CAS parameter or CAS parameter?
你的意思是在我们执行 CAS 之前，
You mean before we actually execute CAS,
但是在我们计算它的参数时？
but while we're computing its arguments?
是的，比如你计算，
Right, so like you compute,
你传入 x 参数，这没问题，
you pass in the x argument and that's okay,
但是在你计算 x+1 之前，
but you before you compute the x plus 1
或者当你在计算 x+1 的时候，
or while you're computing x plus 1,
中断发生了。
an interrupt occurs.
好的。
Okay.
x+1 是错误的。
And the x plus 1 is wrong.
所以，如果在我们计算 x+1 时发生中断，
So, if an interrupt occurs while we're computing x plus 1,
这意味着我们没有，
that means we haven't,
CAS 实际上是一条指令，
CAS is actually an instruction,
它是一条单一的机器指令，
it's a single machine instruction,
所以对于计算 x+1 ，
so for computing x plus 1,
这意味着我们还没有调用 CAS 。
that means we haven't called CAS yet.
如果中断发生，各种事情都可能发生，
If the interrupt happens and all kinds of things may happen,
我们会得到相同的，
we're going to get the same,
如果我们最初在这里读到 0 ，
if we originally read zero here, right,
然后中断或没有中断，
then interrupt or no interrupt,
我们会传递 1 作为第三个参数，
we're gonna pass 1 as this third argument,
因为中断不会改变，
because interrupts not going to [reach out] and change,
这个 x 是这段代码的局部变量，
this is a local, this x is a local variable for this code,
中断上下文，任何事情都不会改变 x 。
so interrupt context which anything is not gonna change x.
所以这意味着我们将传递 0 和 1 ，
So that means we're going to pass 0 and 1 here,
如果 n 仍然是 0 ，
and you know if n is still 0,
那么我们就把它设为 1 ，
then we'll set it to one,
这就是我们想要的，
and that's that's what we want,
如果它不是 0 ，
if it's not still 0,
那么比较并交换不会修改它。
then compare and swap won't change it.
好的，我想你会有问题，
Right, I guess you would have problems,
如果你不设置那个局部变量。
if you didn't set that local variable.
如果你在这里用 l->n ， l->n+1 ，
If you used l l->n here, l->n plus 1,
你肯定会有大麻烦，
you would almost certainly be in big trouble,
因为那样的话， n 随时都可能改变，
because then n could change underfoot at any time,
这就是为什么我们在这里获得一个 n 的拷贝，
that's why we actually grab a copy n,
获取一个拷贝，以固定一个特定值。
grab a copy here in order to fix a specific value.
好的。
Yes.
Okay.
如果有两个读者，
If two readers,
好的，我说一下这种情况，
okay, so I covered the case
不论写者同时调用，
of whatever writer calls the same,
w_lock 与 r_lock 同时调用，
w_lock is called the same time as r_lock,
同样有趣的是，
it's also interesting to wonder
如果同时调用 r_lock 会怎么样。
what if r_lock is called at the same time.
所以假设 n 从 0 开始，
So supposing the n starts at 0,
如果同时调用两个 r_lock ，
we know if two r_locks are called at the same time,
我们想要的是 n 最终的值是 2 ，
what we want is for n to end up with value 2,
两个 r_lock 都返回，
and for both r_locks to return,
这就是我们想要的，
that's what we want,
因为我们希望两个读者能够并行执行，
because we want two readers to, be able to execute in parallel,
能够并行使用数据。
to use the data in parallel.
好的，那么在这一点上，它们都会看到 0 。
Okay, so, they're both gonna see 0 at this point.
所以，在这一点上，它们的 x 都等于 0 ，
So, at this point, both of them are going to have x equal to 0,
它们都会使用 0 和 1 调用比较并交换。
they're both gonna call compare and swap with 0 and 1.
这两个比较和交换中只有一个，
Only one of those two compare and swap hopefully,
恰好有一个比较和交换会成功，
exactly one of those to compare and swaps will succeed,
无论哪一个，
whichever one,
比较和交换是原子指令，
you know compare and swap it's an atomic instruction,
在同一内存位置，它们中只有一个可以发生，
the only one of them happens at a time on a given memory location,
所以无论哪个比较并交换我们先看到，
so whichever will compare and swap is first we'll see,
n 等于 0 ，并将它设置为 1 ，
that n is equal to 0, and will set it to 1,
其他核心同时调用 r_lock ，
the other cores simultaneous call to r_lock,
它的比较和交换然后执行，
it's compare and swap will then execute
在这里它仍然传递 0 和 1 ，
and it'll still pass zero and one here,
但 n 现在将等于 1 ，
but n will now be equal to 1,
所以第二个核心的比较并交换会失败，并返回 0 ，
and so the compare and swap will fail for the second core and return 0,
第二个核心将回到这个循环的顶部，
the second core will go back to the top of this loop,
在这一点上，它将是 1 ，
at this point it will be 1,
那不小于 0 ，
that's not less than zero,
所以我们将继续比较和交换，
so we'll go on to compare and swap,
现在它将传递 1 和 2 ，
and now it'll pass 1 and 2,
现在第二个读锁将会成功，
and now the second read lock will succeed,
他们两个都会有锁。
both of them will have the lock.
所以第一个在第一次尝试时成功了，
So the first one succeeded, the first try,
第二个返回到循环，然后重试。
the second one actually go back to the loop and try again.
有什么问题吗？
Any questions?
哦，抱歉，所以有没有可能，
Oh, sorry, so it is somehow possible that,
所以来了一大堆读取，
so a bunch of reads come,
它们在读取它们的东西，
and they they're reading their stuff,
然后写入也来了，它也想写，
and then a write also comes and it also wants to write,
但是随后一些其他读取，也在写入之后来了，
but then some other reads also come after the write,
但是因为某种原因读取超过了写入，
but then somehow the reads outrun the write,
然后写入还要继续等待。
and the write still has to wait somehow.
是的，所以如果序列是这样的，
Yes, so so if the sequence is that,
一个读者设法获得了锁，
a reader managed to acquire the lock,
一个或多个读者持有锁，
one or more readers have the locks,
现在 n ，它们中的每一个都调用了比较和交换，
now n, you know each of them is called a compare and swap,
对于每个读者，加 1 到 n ，
you know adds one to n for each reader,
所以现在 n 大于 0 ，
so now n is greater than 0,
因为有多个读者，
because there's multiple readers,
如果在这一点上，写入者想要获取锁，
if a writer tries to acquire the lock at this point,
写入者的比较和交换，比较值是 0 ，
the writer's compare and swap, the compare value is 0,
所以，比较和交换会将 n 更改为 -1 ，
so compare and swap will only change n to -1,
只有它的当前值是 0 。
if its current value is 0.
但是我们知道当前值，
But we know the current,
因为有多个读者，
because there's multiple readers,
所以 n 的当前值不是 0 ，
the current value of n is not 0,
所以比较并交换会失败，并返回 0 ，
and so the compare and swap will fail and returns zero,
然后写者在这个循环中，
then the writer will sit here in this loop,
等待 n 等于 0 ，
basically waiting until n is equal to 0,
在比较和交换成功之前，
before it's compare and swap will succeed,
然后返回并将锁交给写入者。
and return and give the lock to the writer.
所以这当然意味着写者可能会饥饿，
So this certainly means the writer can be starved,
有很多读者，可能永远不会是 0 ，
there's a lot of readers and may never be 0
因此写者可能永远不会成功，
and so the write may never succeed,
所以这是这个锁方案的一个缺陷。
so that's a defect in this locking scheme.
谢谢。
Thank you.
我也有一个问题，
I also have a question
关于我刚才提到的两个读者的场景，
about the the two readers scenario that I just mentioned,
似乎在最坏的情况下，
it appears that in the worst case,
第二个到达的读者必须经历循环的另一次迭代
the reader that arrives second has to go through another iteration of the loop,
听起来有点浪费，
sounds somewhat wasteful,
我想知道这是否适用于 n 个写者。
I wonder if this generalizes to n writers.
当然可以。
It's certainly does.
它们都丢失，并重新开始。
They all have to get lost and start again.
你指出了为什么人们不喜欢这个方案，
You put your finger on why people don't like this scheme,
如果有很多同步的读者，
if there's a lot of simultaneous reader,
所以出于你刚才提到的原因，
and so for for the reason you just mentioned,
r_lock ，即使根本没有写者，
r_lock, even if there's no writers at all,
如果有很多读者，在很多核心的读者，
if there's lots of readers, readers on many cores,
r_lock 可能非常非常昂贵，
r_lock can be very very expensive,
关于 r_lock 方案，有一件事你需要知道，
and one thing you need to know about r_lock scheme,
我想我们已经在课堂上提到过，
which I think we've already mentioned in class is that,
在多核系统上，每个核都有关联的缓存，
on a multi-core system, every core has an associated cache,
我们假设 L1 缓存，
we'll say L1 cache,
因此每个内核都有一些缓存内存，
so each core has a bit of cache memory,
不管读或写什么，
and whatever reads or writes something,
它在缓存中，
it's in the cache,
所以可能有许多核心，
so there may be lots and lots of cores,
这里有一种互连网络，
and there's some kind of interconnect network,
允许核心互相交互，
that allows the cores to talk to each other,
因为如果很多核心缓存了一些数据，
because of course if lots of cores have some data cached,
其中一个核心写入那个数据，
and one of the cores writes that data,
写入核心必须告诉其他核心，
the writing core has to tell the other cores,
它们不允许再缓存那个数据，
that they're not allowed to cache the data anymore,
这叫做无效化。
it is called invalidation.
那么，如果你有 n 个读者，会发生什么，
So what actually happens if you have n readers,
人们几乎同时在 n 个内核上调用 r_lock 。
and people calling r_lock at about the same time on n cores.
它们都将读取 n ，抱歉，这个 l->n 值，
They're all gonna read n, sorry this l->n value,
并将这个内存位置加载到它们的缓存中。
and load this memory location into their caches.
它们都会调用比较并交换，
They're all gonna call compare and swap,
第一个调用比较并交换的将修改数据，
what the first one to actually call compare and swap is going to modify the data,
但为了修改数据，
but in order to modify the data
必须使所有其他副本无效，
has to invalidate all these other copies,
所以，比较并交换指令，
and so the compare and swap instruction that,
第一，必须通过这个小网络发送无效化消息，
one has to send out an invalidate message over this little network
到其他 n 个核心的每一个，
to each of the other n cores, right,
然后它返回所有其他核心， n 减去 1 个核心，
and then it returns all the other cores, the n minus 1 cores,
他们的比较并交换必须重新读取，
they have, their compare and swaps now actually have re-read
再次通过网络获取流量，
again requiring traffic over the network,
重新读取这个内存位置的数据，
re-read this data, this memory location,
与 x 相比，他们失败了，
compared with x they have failed,
因为他们都使用 0 调用 x ，
because they all call x with 0,
然后剩余的 n 减去 1 的读者返回到循环的顶部，
then the remaining n minus 1 readers go back to the top of loop,
所有的 n 减去 1 再次读取数据，
and all n minus 1 of them again read the data,x
再次它们中的一个写入，
and again one of them writes it, right,
所以，这里有 n 次循环，
so on each, so there's going to be n times through the loop,
每个核心试着获取锁，
once for each core trying to acquire the lock,
这个循环中的每一次
each of those [trips] through the loop
都涉及网络上的 n 个消息，
involves order n messages on the network,
因为至少 l->n 缓存的每个副本都必须无效。
because at least every copy of the cached l->n has to be invalidated.
这意味着 n 个核心获取锁的总成本，
And that means that the total cost for n cores to acquire a particular lock,
即使对于读取来说，也是 n 阶的，
even for reading is order n,
这意味着当你增加流行数据的核心数量时，
that means as you increase the number of cores for a popular piece of data,
每个只锁一次的费用上升，
the cost for everybody lock it just once goes up,
抱歉，阶数 n 的平方，
sorry, order n squared,
总成本或时间，或通过这个互连发送的是 n 的平方。
the total cost and time or messages sent over this interconnect is n squared.
这是一笔非常糟糕的决定，
And this is a very bad deal, right,
你希望，
you would hope that,
如果你需要做一件事十次，
if you needed to do something ten times,
十个不同的核心需要做一些事情，
you know ten different cores needed to do something,
特别是它们只是在读取列表，
especially given that they're just reading the list,
它们没有修改，
they're not modifying it,
你希望它们真的能并行运行，
you'd hope that they could really run in parallel,
这是 16 个核心读取数据的总时间，
that is the total [] clock time for 16 cores to read something,
应该与一个核心读取某件东西的总时间相同，
should be the same as the total [] clock time for one core read something,
因为这是并行性的意思，
because that's getting parallelism means is that,
你可以同时做一些事情。
you can do things at the same time.
但在这里，更多的内核读取这个，
But here the more cores are try to read this,
获取锁的成本就越高，
the more expensive the lock acquisition is,
所以现在的情况是，
and so what's going on is that,
这种类型的锁已转换为对数据的只读访问，
this style of locks has converted read only access to data,
这个列表可能已经在缓存里了，
you know the list is probably sitting in the cache already,
因为没有人修改列表。
because nobody's modifying the list, right.
所以对列表的访问可能只需要几十个周期，
So the actual access to the list might only take a few dozen cycles,
但是如果数据很受欢迎，
but if the data is popular,
获取锁可能需要数百或数千个周期，
getting the lock can take hundreds or thousands of cycles,
因为这个 n 平方效应。
because of this n squared effect.
并且它不是缓存 x ，
And the fact that instead of it being cache x,
这些访问必须通过总线，这个互连，
it's these accesses that have to go over the bus, this interconnect,
以便无效化，做缓存一致性操作。
in order to invalidate and do these cache coherence operations.
所以这些锁对数据的只读访问变得非常便宜，
So this these locks have turned very cheap read only access to data,
转换为对这个数据的极其昂贵的读写访问。
into an extremely expensive read write access to this data.
并且可能会完全破坏任何可能的并行性能，
And will probably completely destroy any possible parallel performance,
如果你在做什么，
if what you were doing,
如果实际数据很容易读取，
if the actual data was fairly simple to read,
锁将主导并破坏并行性能。
lock will dominate and destroy parallel performance.
关于这个性能故事，有什么问题吗？
So any questions about this performance story?
从某种意义上说，读写锁的糟糕性能，
In a sense you know the bad performance of read write locks
是 RCU 存在的原因，
is the reason for the existence of RCU,
因为如果这是有效的，
because if this was efficient,
那么就没有必要比那个做得更好了，
then there would be no need to do better than that right,
但是它的效率非常低。
but it's terribly inefficient.
有两件事正在发生，
And it's there's two things going on,
一个是这个的细节，
one is the details of this,
在这个循环中总共需要 n 平方的行程，
so there needs to be a total of n squared trips through this loop,
如果我们有 n 个核心，
if we have n cores,
这是一种看待它的方式。
sort of one way of looking at it.
另一种看待它的方式是，
The other way of looking at it is that,
我们写入，
we're writing,
不管这里发生了什么事的细节，
you know regardless of the details of what's going on here,
这些锁变为只读访问，
these locks have turned a read only access,
这可能会缓存，并且速度极快，
which could be cached and extremely fast
进入这样或那样[涉及]写入，
into an access that one way or another involves a write,
一个或多个写入，
one or more writes,
而写入比读取要昂贵得多，
and writes are just much more expensive than reads,
如果我们写入可能与其他内核共享的数据。
if we're writing data that might be shared with other cores.
因为读取没有修改数据，
Because a read for data that's not modify,
它可以在几个周期内从你的缓存中得到，
it can be satisfied in a couple cycles out of your own cache,
对其他核心缓存的数据的任何写入，
a write, any write to data that may be cached by other cores,
必须涉及内核之间的通信以使其他副本无效。
has to involve communication between cores to invalidate other copies.
所以不管你怎么切分它，
So no matter how you slice it,
任何涉及写入共享数据的行为都会对性能造成灾难，
anything that involves a write to share data is a disaster for performance,
否则，你可能只是只读的。
if you otherwise could have been read only.
所以这个循环的细节，
So the details of this loop,
没有比写入共享数据那么重要。
are sort of less important than the fact that it did a write to share data.
所以我们要找的是一种方法，
So what we're looking for is a way
不需要写入就能读取数据的方法，
to be able to read data without writes, right,
我们希望能够在不执行任何写入的情况下扫描列表，
we want to be able to scan that list without doing any writes,
不包括任何写入，
what so ever, including any writes,
可能需要执行某种锁，
that might be required to do some kind of locking thing,
它们寻找对数据的真正的只读访问。
they were looking for really really read only access to data.
好的。
Okay.
所以有一种可能，
So one possibility, that's a possibility,
但这是一种思维实验，
but it's sort of a thought experiment is
我们只是让读者不用关心加锁，
we just have the readers not bother locking,
偶尔你很幸运，
you know occasionally you get lucky
发现读者可以读到一些东西，
and it turns out that readers can read stuff,
只有写者才需要加锁。
and that only writers need to lock.
所以我们做个快速实验看看，
So we'll just do a quick experiment to see,
我们是否可以有一个锁，
whether we could have a lock,
让读者读取列表而不加锁。
just have readers just read the list without locking it.
我想我们有这个列表，它有一些字符串。
I suppose we have this list and it has some you know strings.
而且，我们要读取它，
And, we're gonna read it,
如果没有正确的写入者，就不会出问题，
okay, so nothing goes wrong if there's no writer, right,
只需要读取列表，不会有问题。
just read list, it's not a problem.
所以我们想象有一个写者，
So we have to imagine there's a writer,
可能有三种情况，
and there's probably three cases,
如果你读取一个列表，在一些其他内核正在修改列表时，
if you read a list while some other cores modifying it,
所以，一种情况是，
so one case is that,
写者只是在改变内容，
the writer is just changing the content,
就是不增加或者删除任何元素，
that is not adding or deleting anyone is necessarily,
写者将字符串更改为其他字符串。
a writer is changing the string to be some other string.
所以，一是，写者改变了内容，
So, one is the writers changing the content,
二是，写者插入新的列表元素，
two is the writer is inserting a new list element,
第三种情况是，写者删除列表元素。
and the third case is if the writer is deleting a list element.
我想检查一下这些，
And I want to examine these,
因为我们需要每个 RCU 有一个[故事]，
because we need a [story] for each of RCU
每个 RCU 都有一个[故事]。
actually kind of has a [story] for each.
所以，危险，
So, the danger,
所以我只是在说会出什么问题，
so I'm just talking about what goes wrong,
如果有人在读取列表，而另一个核心在写入它，
if somebody's reading a list while another cores writing it,
如果写者只想更改这个字符串，
if the writer wants to just change this string,
那么危险在于读者将读取这个字符串的字节，
then the danger is that the reader will be actually reading the bytes of this string
或者列表元素中的任何其他内容，
or whatever else is in the list element,
而写者正在修改相同的字节。
while the writer is modifying the same bytes.
所以如果我们不做些特别的事，
And so if we don't do anything special,
读者将看到旧字节和新字节的某种混合，
the reader will see some mixture of the old bytes and the new bytes,
这可能是一场灾难，
and that's probably a disaster,
这是我们要担心的一种情况。
that's one case we have to worry about.
另一种可能性是写者插入新元素，
Another possibility is that the writer is inserting a new element,
当然，这意味着，
of course what that means is that,
假设写者想要在头部插入新元素，
you know supposing the writer wants to insert the new element at the head,
写者将编造一些新的元素，
the writers going to cook up some new element
并改变头指针指向它，
going to change the head pointer to point to it,
我要将新元素更改为指向旧的第一个元素，
I'm going to change the new element to point at the old first element, right,
所以这里的危险是，
so the danger here,
如果读者读取列表，当写者在插入，
if a reader reads, reading list while writers inserting,
也许如果我们真的搞砸了，
is that maybe you know if we really blow it,
写者可以将头指针设置为指向新元素，
the the writer may set the head pointer to point to the new element,
在新元素初始化之前，
before the new elements initialized,
这就是为什么它可能包含字符串的垃圾，
that is why it may be contains garbage for the string
或一些非法指针作为下一个元素。
or some illegal pointer as the next element.
这就是写者插入时可能出错的地方。
So that's the thing that could go wrong for writer's inserting.
所以让我们，写者删除，
So let's, and the writer's deleting,
那么，删除元素意味着，
then, you know what it means to delete an element
比如说删除第一个元素，
is first to change let's say deleting the first element,
我们将头指针更改为指向第二个元素，
we change the head pointer to point to the second element,
然后在第一个元素上调用释放，
and then call free on the first element
将其返回到空闲列表，
to return this to the free list,
这里的危险是，
and the danger here,
如果读者看到新的头指针，那很好，
you know if the reader sees the new head pointer, that's fine,
他们只会继续第二个元素，
they're just gonna go on to the second element,
所以，如果读者正在查找第一个元素，
so the first if the reader actually was looking at the first element
然后写者释放了它，
and then the writer freed it,
那么我们遇到的问题是，
then the problem we have is
现在读者查看空闲列表中的元素，
now the readers looking at element that's on the free list,
可以被分配用于一些其他用途，
and could be allocated for some other use
并且被重写用于一些完全其他的用途，
and overwritten for some completely other use,
当读者还在查看这个元素的时候。
while the readers still looking at this element.
所以从读者的角度来看，
So from the reader point of view,
现在所有的元素突然充满了垃圾，
now all of a sudden elements filled with garbage
并说它正在期待，
and said it was [expecting],
所以这是第三种情况，我们必须。
so that's the third case, we have to.
如果我们想加锁，
If we want to have lock,
我们想要的是对读者绝对没有锁，
we want have absolutely no locks for readers,
我们要担心这三种情况。
we have to worry about these three situations.
我不是在说写者和写者之间的问题，
I'm not talking about writer versus writer problems here,
我假设在整节课中，
because I'm just assuming for this entire lecture,
写者仍在使用锁，
that writers still use locks,
这里还有一些普通的像 xv6 的自旋锁，
there's still some ordinary like xv6 style spin lock here,
写者在做任何事情之前就获得这个锁，
and writers acquire this lock before doing anything,
但是读者无论如何都不需要任何锁。
but readers don't require any locks, whatsoever.
关于这些危险，有什么问题？
Questions about these dangers?
好的。
Okay.
关键是我们不能简单地让读者不加锁地读取，
The point is we can't just simply have readers read with no locks,
但是我们可以解决这个问题，
but it turns out we can and fix the specific problems,
这把我们带到了 RCU 。
and that takes us to RCU.
RCU 有几个想法，
RCU has a couple of ideas in it that,
顺便说一句， RCU 是一种并发控制的方法，
RCU is, by the way, it's as much a kind of approach to concurrency, concurrency control
因为它是一种特定的算法，
as it is a particular algorithm,
这是一种构建读者和写者的方式。
it's a way of structuring approach structuring readers and writers.
这样它们可以与读者相处，而不用加锁。
So that they can get along with the readers not having to take locks.
读取复制更新的一般游戏是，
The general game with read copy update is
我们将修复这三种情况，
we're going to fix those three situations,
如果同时有写者的话，读者可能会遇到麻烦，
in which readers might get into trouble if there's a concurrent writers,
我们将通过让写者变得更复杂一点来做到这一点。
and we're going to do it by making the writers a little bit more complicated.
所以写者会稍微慢一点，
So the writers going to end up somewhat slower,
它们仍然需要加锁并遵守一些额外的规则，
they still need to lock plus follow some extra rules,
但回报是读者的速度将会大大提高，
but the reward will be the readers will be dramatically faster,
因为它们可以在没有锁的情况下操作，
because they can operate without locks
也不需要写入内存。
and without ever writing memory.
好的， RCU 的第一个想法是，
Okay, so the first big idea in RCU is that,
在我们之前讨论的第一个麻烦的情况下，
in that first trouble situation, we talked about before,
写者更新列表元素，列表元素的内容，
where the writer is updating a list element, the content of a list element,
我们要[取消]它，
we're going to actually outlaw that,
我们说写者不允许修改列表元素的内容，
we're going to say writers are not allowed to modify the contents of a list elements,
相反，如果我们有一个这样的链表，有几个元素。
instead if we have a linked list like this, with a couple of elements.
如果写者想要更新元素 2 的内容，
If a writer wanted to update the content of element 2,
不是原地修改它，我们不这么做，
instead of changing it in place, which wouldn't do,
它会调用分配器来分配一个新的元素，
it would actually cook up, it would call the allocator to allocate a new element,
它将完全初始化元素，
it would initialize the element completely,
所以不管我们想在这里放什么新内容，
so whatever new content you know we wanted to put here,
不是老的内容，
instead the old content,
写者将在新元素上设置下一个指针，
the writer would set the next pointer on this new element,
所以这个新元素现在看起来完全正确了，
so that this new element is now completely correct looking,
然后在对 E1 的下一个指针的单次写入，
and then in a single write to E1's next pointer,
写者将切换 E1 指向，
the writer would switch E1 from pointing to the,
从指向 E2 的旧版本，
from pointing to the old version of E2,
指向 E2 的新版本。
to pointing to the new version of E2.
所以这个游戏是不原地更新内容，
So the game is instead of updating things in place,
我们用相同数据的新版本替换它们。
we're going to replace them with new versions of the same data.
所以现在一个读者得到了 E1 ，
And so so now a reader, you know readers got as far as E1
只是查看 E1 的下一个指针，
is just looking at E1's next pointer,
读者将看到指向 E2 的旧的下一个指针，
the reader's going to either see the old next pointer which points to E2
这很好，
and that's fine,
因为没有人改变 E2 ，
because nobody was changing E2,
或者读者会看到新的下一个指针，
or the reader's going to see the new next pointer
然后看到新的列表元素。
and look at the new list element.
无论哪种方式，因为写者完全初始化了这个列表元素，
And either way since the writer initial fully initialized this list element,
在设置 E1 的下一个指针之前，
before setting E1's next pointer,
无论哪种方式，读者都会看到正确的下一个指针，指向 E3 的指针。
either way, the readers going to see a correct next pointer, that points to E3.
所以重点是读者永远看不到字符串，
So the point is the reader will never see a string,
在内容被修改的过程中（的字符串）。
that's in the process of being a content that's in the process of being modified.
对这个特别的想法，有什么问题吗？
There's any questions about this particular idea?
那这个，抱歉。
What about the, sorry.
好的，我可以先说，
Okay, I can go ahead,
E2 和 E3 之间的连接是否会被删除，
will the the link between E2 and E3 be deleted,
或者它会留在那里，
or will it be left there
以防它们以某种方式到达 E2 。
in case that are either somehow reached E2.
现在，我们就不管它了，
Now, we're just gonna leave it,
好的，我会回到这个很棒的问题，
well I'll come to this, this excellent question,
这实际上是 RCU 最复杂的部分，
and it's actually the main piece of complexity in RCU,
但现在我们想象一下 E2 暂时不会出现。
but for now we're just going to imagine that E2 is left alone for the moment.
从 E2 到 E3 的连接，我们不用担心，对吧，
The link from E2 to E3 we don't need to worry about it anyway right,
因为这是 E2 的一部分，
because that's a part of E2,
就像在正常的实现中，
and like in normal implementations,
我们无论如何都要释放它，
we just free that anyway,
比如不涉及 RCU 时，
like with no RCU involved,
我们永远不需要担心那个连接，对吧。
we don't ever need to worry about that link, right.
但危险在于，
But the danger is that,
在我们改变下一个指针之前，
that just before we changed this next pointer,
一些读者跟随下一个指向 E2 的指针。
that some reader had followed the next pointer to E2.
总体而言，我们在这里担心的是，
So overall what we're worried about here is that,
一些核心上的读者现在正在读取 E2 ，
some some reader on some cores actually right now reading E2,
所以我们最好不要释放它。
so we'd better not free it.
好的，好的。
Right right.
我想这就是我们要说的，
That's what I think that's all we're saying is
你最好不要马上释放 E2 ，
you better not free E2 right away,
只是别管它了。
just leave it alone.
作为一个术语，
As a piece of jargon,
这个写入，
the write,
E1 的下一个指针从旧的 E2 到新的 E2 的交换，
the swap of e E1's next pointer from the old E2 to the new E2,
在我的脑海里把这叫做提交写入，
I in my head I call this a committing write,
这有一个，
there's a,
这个可以工作的部分原因是，
this is then part of the reason why this works is that,
使用单个提交写入，这是原子的，
with a single committing write, which is atomic,
在我们使用的机器上的指针的写入是原子的，
writes to pointers on the machines we use are atomic,
写入指针发生或不发生，
in the sense that either the write to the pointer happen or didn't happen,
从读者的角度看，
from the perspective of readers,
因为它们是原子的，
because they're atomic,
是一个指令，
basically with one instruction,
只有一个原子的保存，
with the one atomic store we can,
这是一个普通的保存，
it's an ordinary store,
但它是不可分割的，
but it's indivisible,
我们把 E1 切换为指向旧的，
we switch E1 from point to old,
下一个指向旧的那个，
the next point from pointing to the old one,
写入的新的版本提交到，
the new one that write is what sort of commits us to,
现在使用第二个版本。
now using the second version.
这是一种非常基本的技术，
This is a very basic technique,
是 RCU 的一项非常重要的技术，
a very important technique for RCU,
这意味着，
and what it means is that,
RCU 主要适用于数据结构，
RCU is really mostly applicable to data structures,
你可以对它进行单次提交写入。
for which you can have single committing writes.
这意味着方案中有一些数据结构相当笨拙，
So that means there's some data structures which are quite awkward in the scheme,
比如双向链表，
like a doubly linked list,
其中每个元素都从两个不同的指针指向，
where every element is pointed to from two different pointers,
现在我们不能通过一次提交写入来删除列表元素，
now we can't get rid of a list elements with a single committing write,
因为这里有两个指向它的指针，
because there's two pointers to it,
在大多数机器上，我们不能原子地
we can't, on most machines we can't atomically
同时修改两个不同的内存位置，
change two different memory locations at the same time,
所以，双链表对 RCU 并不是那么好。
so doubly lists are not so good for RCU.
好的数据结构是像树一样的，
A data structure that is good as a tree,
如果你有一个树，
and if you have a tree of,
像这样的节点树，
a tree of nodes like this,
然后我们可以做，
then we can do,
假设我们想要改变，
suppose we want to change,
想要修改这里的值，
want to modify this value down here,
我们能做的是，
what we can do,
这里有一个指向树的头，
there's some head to the tree,
我们能做的是
what we can do is
在这棵树的这部分做一个新的版本，
cook up a new a new version of this part of the tree here,
并且利用对头指针的单个提交写入，
and with a single committing write to the head pointer,
切换到树的新版本，
switch to the new version of the tree,
所以这棵树的新版本，
and so the new version of the tree,
写者将分配，创建，
which will you know the writer will allocate, sort of create,
可以方便地共享数据结构，
can actually share for, convenience share structure,
老的树的未修改的部分，
the unmodified part with the old tree,
然后利用单个提交写入，
and then with a single committing write,
我们将把头指针更改为
we're going to change the head pointer to
树的头指针指向新版本。
a tree head pointer to point to the new version.
但是对于其他数据结构，
But for other data structures,
它们不像树一样，
that don't look like the trees,
使用 RCU 并不容易。
it's not so easy to use RCU.
好的，这是第一个想法。
Okay, that's the first idea.
还有其他问题吗？
Any other questions?
第二个想法，
The second idea,
这里的一个问题，
One of the problems with,
一个关于我提到的方案的问题，
one of the potential problems with this scheme I just described,
我们要创建一个新的 E2 ，
and we're gonna cook up a new E2 [],
我说的是，我们将初始化 E2 的内容，
and what I said was oh well we'll initialize the content for E2 [],
我们会设置它的下一个指针，
and we'll you know set its next pointer, correctly,
然后，我们将 E1 的下一个指针设置为指向 E2 ，
and after that we'll set E1's next pointer to point to E2,
你可能还记得在讨论 xv6 时，
as you may recall from discussions of xv6,
默认情况下，这些机器上没有这个选项，
by default, there's no after that on these machines,
编译器和硬件，
the compiler and the hardware,
基本上所有编译器和许多微处理器对内存操作重新排序。
basically all compilers and many microprocessors reorder memory operations.
所以，如果你简单地分配一个新元素，
So, if you simply you know say we allocate a new element,
我们写一段 C 代码， e->next 等于 E3 ，
and we just wrote this C code, you know e->next equals you know E3,
然后 E1->next 等于 e ，
and then E1->next equals e,
这不会成功工作，
this is not going to work well,
它不会可靠地工作，
it's not gonna work reliably,
当你测试它的时候，它会工作的很好，
it's gonna work fine when you test it,
但它在现实中并不总是有效的，
but it won't work in real life all the time,
偶尔也会出问题。
occasionally it will go wrong.
原因是编译器可能会重新排序这些写入，
And the reason is that the compiler may end up reordering these writes
或者机器可能会重新排序这些写入，
or the machine may end up reordering these writes
或者读取代码读取这些不同内容，
or the reading code which reads these various things,
编译器或机器，微处理器可能会对读者的读取重新排序，
the compiler or the machine, the microprocessor may end up reordering the reader's reads,
当然，如果我们将 E1->next 设置为指向 E2 ，
and of course if we set E1->next to point E2
在我们在初始化 E2 的内容之前，
before we initialize the content of E2,
它的字符串包含下一个指针，指向[空格]，
so that it's string holds its next pointer, point off into space,
然后一些读者会看到这个指针，
then some readers going to see this pointer,
随后是读取垃圾和崩溃。
follow with read garbage and crash.
所以第二个想法是，
So the second idea is that,
读者和写者都必须使用内存屏障，
both readers and writers have to use memory barriers,
即使我们没有加锁，
you know even though we're not locking or really because we're not locking,
写者和读者都要用屏障，
read, the writers and the readers have to use a barrier,
而对于写者来说，屏障必须是在提交写入之前。
and for writers the place the barrier has to go is before the committing write.
所以我们这里需要一个屏障，
So we need a barrier here,
告诉硬件和编译器，在屏障之前的所有写入，
tells the hardware and the compiler look all the writes before this barrier,
请先完成它们，在做任何屏障之后的写入之前。
please finish them before doing any writes after the barrier.
所以， E2 已完全初始化，
So that E2 is fully initialized,
在我们将 E1 设置为指向它之前。
before we set E1 to point to it.
在读取端，
And on the read side,
读者需要将 E1->next 加载到某个临时位置或寄存器中，
the reader needs to load E1->next into some temporary location or register,
所以我们就说寄存器 1 等于 E1->next ，
so we'll just say register one equals E1->next,
然后读者需要一个屏障，
then the reader needs a barrier,
然后读者会查看 r1->x ，
and then the reader is going to look at r1->x,
r1->next 中的内容。
it's content in r1->next.
有了这个屏障，读者表示的是，
And with this barrier, the reader says is
在我们完成这个加载之前，不要发出任何加载。
don't issue any of these loads until after we've completed this load.
所以读者要查看 E1->next ，
So the reader's gonna look at E1->next
要么得到旧的 E2 ，要么得到新的 E2 ，
and either get the old E2 or the new E2,
然后屏障表示，
and then the barrier says that,
只有到那时，我们才开始看，
only then are we going to start looking at,
只有在那之后，我们拿到这个，
only after we've grabbed this,
所有这些读取都必须在这个读取之后执行。
all these reads have to execute after this read.
并且由于写者保证初始化内容
And since the writer guaranteed to initialize the content
在提交指向新 E2 的指针之前，
before committing the pointer to the new E2,
这意味着这些读取，
that means these reads,
如果这个指针指向新的 E2 ，
if this pointer points to the new E2,
这意味着这些读取保证可以看到初始化的内容。
that means these reads are guaranteed to see the initialized content.
好的，我们看了一点。
Okay, so we saw a little bit.
你怎么能，哦，抱歉，
How can you, oh sorry,
我对读者感到困惑，
I was just, I was confused about the reader,
所以，你么读取 r1 ，
so how, how can you read r1,
比如任何在 r1 之前的东西。
r1 like anything before you read r1.
我猜它们会怎么，
I guess how how would they,
所以，我想即使它能带来回报，
so yeah, I guess like if even if it rewarded that,
如何能够在读取 r1->next 之前读取 r1->x ？
how, how did be able to read r1->x before it read r1->next?
我想你把我难倒了。
You, I think you've stumped me.
我是说你刚才指出的是，
Yeah, I mean what were you pointing out is that,
在你不知道指针是什么之前，
before you even know what the pointer is
你不可能发出读取，
you can't possibly actually issue the reads,
一种可能性是，无论这个指针指向什么，
the, a possibility is that whatever this pointer points to,
也许它已经缓存在这个核心上了，
maybe it's already cached on this core,
因为一些可能这段内存曾经，
due to some maybe this memory had been
一分钟前用来做其他完全不同的事情，
you know a minute ago used for something else, something totally else,
我们有一个旧版本的缓存在核心中，
and we have an old version of this cache our core,
在这个地址上，
at the address at this address,
但是对于内存的某些先前使用，
but for some previous use of the memory,
如果这个读取要使用旧的缓存值，
if this read was to use the old cache value,
我不确定这会不会发生，
I'm not sure this can happen,
只是为你编造的。
just making this up for you.
但是如果这真的可以使用旧的缓存值，
But if this really could use the old cache value,
那么我们就有大麻烦了。
then we'd be in big trouble.
我不知道机器是否真的能做到这一点。
And I don't know if the machine would actually do that or whether.
另一种可能性是编译器，
Another possibility is that the compiler,
真正的答案是我不知道，
you know, the real answer is I don't know,
我应该停下，想一想具体的例子是什么。
I should go off and think about what a specific example would be.
好的，我明白了，缓存版本，理解了，是的。
Okay, okay, I see, the cache version, makes sense, yeah.
我并不完全确定这是否会在现实生活中发生。
I'm not actually completely sure it could could happen in real life.
这是个好问题。
That's a good question.
好的，这是第二个想法。
Okay, that's the second idea.
第三个问题，之前有人提到了，
The third problem we have which something somebody raised before
写者会切换 E1 指针指向新的 E2 ，
is that the writer is going to swap the E1 pointer to point to the new E2,
但可能会有读者，开始查找这个指针，
but there could be readers, you know who started looking at follow this pointer,
就在写者修改之前，
just before we change the writer changed,
它仍在查看 E2 。
who are still looking at E2.
总有一天，我们要释放这个列表元素，
We need to free this list element someday,
但是我们最好不要在一些读者还在使用的时候释放它，
but we'd better not free it while some readers still using it,
所以，我们需要以某种方式等待，
so we need to somehow wait
直到最后一个读者使用完 E2 ，
until the last reader has finished using E2,
然后才能释放它。
before we can free it.
这是 RCU 解决的第三个也是最后一个主要问题，
And that's the third and final main problem that RCU solves,
写者应该等待多长时间才能释放 E2 。
how long should a writer wait before it frees E2.
你可以想象有很多方法可以做到这一点，
There's you could imagine a number of ways of doing this,
比如，我们可以在每个列表元素中添加一些引用计数，
for example we could put a reference count in every list element
并让读者递增它，
and have readers increment it,
并让写者等待，
and have writers wait,
读者在开始使用列表元素时递增，
reader's increment when they start using list element,
在使用列表元素完成后，将其递减，
decrement it, when they're done using the list element,
让写者等待这个元素上的引用计数变为 0 ，
and have the writer wait for the reference count on this element go to 0,
我们很快会后悔，
we would regret that instantly,
因为 RCU 的全部意义在于允许读而不用写。
because the whole point of RCU is to allow reading without writing.
因为如果很多读者改变这个引用计数，
Because we know that if lots of readers are changing this reference count
维护引用计数所涉及的写入会非常昂贵，
is going to be terribly expensive to do the writes involved in maintaining a reference count,
所以我们绝对不想要引用计数。
so we absolutely don't want reference counts.
另一种可能性是使用垃圾收集语言，
Another possibility would be to use a garbage collected language,
对于垃圾收集语言来说，
and in a garbage collected language,
你从来没有明确释放过任何东西，
you don't ever free anything explicitly,
取而代之的是，垃圾收集器负责所需的记账工作，
instead the garbage collector does the bookkeeping required
以确定是否有任何线程
to decide if any thread
或任何数据结构仍具有对这个元素的引用，
for example any data structure has still has a reference to this element,
垃圾收集器一旦证明这个元素不可能再被使用，
and the garbage collector once it proves this element can't possibly be ever used again,
只有到那时垃圾收集器才会将其释放，
only then will the garbage collector free this,
所以，这是另一种合理的方案。
so that's another quite possibly reasonable scheme
决定何时释放这个列表元素。
for deciding when to free this list element.
你知道使用 RCU 的 Linux ，
You know Linux which uses RCU,
它不是用垃圾收集语言编写的。
it's not written in a garbage collected language, so.
我们甚至不确定垃圾收集是否会提高性能，
And we're not even sure that garbage collection would be would improve performance,
所以我们不能在这里使用标准的垃圾收集器，
so we can't use a standard garbage collector here,
取而代之， RCU 使用了另一种技巧，
instead, RCU uses another sort of a trick,
在内核中可以很好地工作，即[延迟冻结]。
that works well in the kernel for delaying freeze.
所以这个想法是，
And so that idea is that,
读者和写者，每个都必须遵守一条规则，
the readers and writers have to each follow a rule,
这将允许写者推迟冻结，
that will allow writers to delay the freeze,
读者不允许在上下文切换期间持有指向 RCU 保护数据的指针。
readers are not allowed to hold a pointer to RCU protected data across a context switch.
因此读者不允许持有指针，
So a reader is not allowed to hold a pointer,
在上下文切换时，那些列表元素中的一个。
one of those list elements across a context switch.
所以，读者不能在 RCU 临界区中让出 CPU 。
So the readers, they cannot yield the CPU, in a RCU critical section.
然后写者要做的是，
And then what the writers do is,
它们将释放延迟到每个核心至少切换一次上下文。
they delay the free until every core as context switches at least once.
所以这很简单，
So this is easy enough,
这实际上也是自旋锁的一条规则，
this is actually also a rule for spin locks,
在自旋锁定临界区，你不能让出 CPU ，
in a spin lock critical section, you can't yield the CPU,
但不管怎样，你还是要小心一点。
but nevertheless you have to be a bit careful.
这有点牵涉其中，
This is a little more involved,
但是，情况相对清楚，
but it's relatively clear,
当每个核心都知道这种上下文切换，
when each each cores knows this context switching,
所以，这是写者必须等待的一个非常明确的点。
and so this is a pretty well defined point for the writer to have to wait for.
只需要一些实现，
And just requires some implementation,
这也要求，这可能是一个很大的延迟，
this also requires this may be a significant delay
可能是一毫秒或一毫秒的重要部分，
and maybe a millisecond or a significant fraction of a millisecond
写者必须等待，在被允许释放这个列表元素之前，
that the writer has to wait, before it's allowed to free that list element,
以确保没有读者可能还在使用它。
to be sure that no reader could possibly still be using it.
人们已经想出了一系列技术来实现这种等待，
People have come up with a bunch of techniques for actually implementing this wait,
这篇论文谈到的最直截了当的一点是，
though most straightforward one the paper talks about is that,
写入线程简单地与调度器一起安排，
the writing thread simply arranges with the scheduler
以使写入线程在系统中的每个核心上短暂地执行。
to have the writing thread be executed briefly on every one of the cores in the system.
这意味着，
And what that means is that
在这个过程中，每个核新都必须进行上下文切换，
every one of the cores must have done a context switch during this process,
而且由于读者不能跨上下文切换持有内容，
and since readers can't hold stuff across context switches,
这意味着写者现在已经等得够久了。
that means that the writer is now waited long enough.
所以，写者代码看起来是这样的，
And so the way the actual writer code looks like is
写入代码对数据进行任何修改，
the writing code does whatever modifications it's going to do to the data,
然后它调用这个 synchronize_rcu 调用，
and then it calls this synchronize_rcu call,
它实现了 2 。
which actually implements 2.
然后写者冻结旧元素。
And then the writer freeze whatever the old element was.
所以这意味着写者做任何它在做的事情，
And so that means that the writer is doing whatever it's doing,
在这一点上，
you know at this point,
假设它正在执行 E1->next 等于新的列表元素。
let's say it's doing the you know the E1->next is equal to the new list element.
这个 synchronize_rcu 会在每个核心上强制执行上下文切换，
And so you know this synchronize_rcu causes force a context switch on every core,
所以任何核心可以读取，
so any core that could have read,
任何核心可以读取旧的值，
any core that could have read the old value,
在这一点上，一定已经读取了它，
must have read it at this point,
一定是在这个时间点上读取过了，
must have read it at this point in time,
如果在这个时间点之后，
if after that point in time,
我们已经在每个核心做了上下文切换，
we've done a context switch on every core,
这意味着，没有读取旧值的核心，
that means that no core that read the old value
在这个时间点上仍然具有指向这个值的指针，
could still have a pointer to that value at this point in time,
基于规则 1 ，
due to rule one,
这意味着它们允许释放旧的值。
and that means they were allowed to free the old value.
有什么问题吗？
Any questions?
你可能会反对这个 synchronize_rcu
You may object that this synchronize_rcu
将花费相当大的可能零点几毫秒时间，
will take a significant perhaps fraction of a millisecond,
这是非常正确的。
that's quite true.
是这样的，所以这太糟糕了，
Is that, so that's too bad,
其中一个理由是写入 RCU 保护的数据，
one of the justifications is that writing for RCU protected data,
写入将会变得相对罕见，
writing is going to be relatively rare,
所以，写入时间较长
so the fact that the writes take longer
可能不会对整体性能产生太大影响，
may not will probably not affect overall performance very much,
对于写者不想等待的情况，
for the situations in which the writer really doesn't want to wait,
还有另一个调用，
there's another call,
它可以延迟等待，叫做 call_rcu 。
that that defers even a wait call call_rcu.
这里的想法是，在通常的情况中，
And the idea is you pass it the, in the usual use case,
你可以向它传递一个指向要释放的对象的指针，
you pass it a pointer to the object you want to free,
然后一个回调函数调用释放这个指针，
and then a callback function that just calls free on this pointer,
而 RCU 系统会藏起来，
and the rcu system basically stashes away,
call_rcu 在列表上把这两个值[藏起来]，
the call_rcu stashes away these two values on list,
然后立即返回，然后做一些记录，
and then immediately returns and then does some bookkeeping,
通常涉及查看每个核心上
typically involving basically looking at
已经发生了多少上下文的计数，
the counts of how many contexts which have occurred on each core,
在调用 call_rcu 返回后，
the system, sort of in the background after call_rcu returns
做一些[记账]等待，直到所有核心上下文切换，
does some bookkeeping to wait until all cores context switch,
然后使用这个参数调用这个回调函数，
and then calls this callback function with this argument,
所以这是避免等待的一种方式，
and so this is a way of avoiding the wait,
因为这个调用马上就会返回。
because this call returns instantly.
另一方面，你会被劝阻不要使用它，
On the other hand, you're discouraged from using it,
因为现在这个列表，
because now this list that,
如果内核大量调用 call_rcu ，
if if the kernel calls call_rcu a lot,
那么保存这些值的列表可能会变得非常长，
then the list that holds these values can get very long,
这意味着可能会有大量的内存不会被释放，
and it means that there may be a lot of memory that's not being freed,
所有数据，
all the data all the,
这个列表变得很长，
this, this list grows very long,
每个列表元素中都有一个应该释放的指针，
each list element of is has a pointer in it that should be free
指向应该释放的对象。
to point to an object that should be freed.
所以在极端情况下，
So under extreme circumstances,
你可以运行一个系统，
you can run a system,
如果你不注意 call_rcu 的大量调用，
if you're not careful a lot of calls to rcu call_rcu,
你运行的系统会内存不足，
you can run a system out of memory,
因为所有的内存最终都会出现在这个延迟冻结的列表上。
because all the memory ends up on this list of deferred freeze.
所以人们不喜欢用这个，他们没必要。
So people don't like to use this, they don't have to.
好的，
Okay, to,
到目前为止，如果你有问题，请提问。
please ask questions so far, if you have questions.
所以，这会阻止我们释放，
So, this doesn't, this prevents us free,
阻止我们释放别人仍在使用的东西，
that prevents us from freeing something that somebody's still using,
这并不阻止我们修改，
it doesn't prevent us from modified,
比如读者看到某个东西的半个的版本，
like having the readers see a half-baked version of something,
因为它被修改了。
because it's being modified right.
想法 1 阻止了那个。
Idea 1 prevented that, yeah.
好的。
Okay.
所以想法 1 的背后是，
So they they get the idea, behind the idea 1 is that,
不是就地更新列表元素，
instead of updating a list element in place,
这绝对会导致你提到的问题，
which would absolutely cause the problem you mentioned,
写者不允许就地更新 RCU 保护的数据，
when the writers are not allowed to update RCU protected data in place,
相反，它们创造了一个新的数据元素，
instead they cook up a new data element,
将其交换到数据结构中，只需一次提交写入。
and sort of swap it into the data structure with a single committing write.
哦，而且交换是原子的，
Oh, and the swapping will be atomic,
所以没问题。
so there's no problem.
是的，因为这是一个单指针，它是原子的，
Right, because that's a single pointer, right, which is atomic,
而重写字符串完全不是原子的。
whereas overwriting a string is completely not atomic.
理解了。
That makes sense.
还有其他问题吗？
Other questions?
想法 3 中的条件 1 是否意味着
Does condition 1 in idea 3 mean
我们在这些受保护部分中投入了多少工作，
we need to be careful about how much work we put inside those protected sections,
因为它占据了整个区域的核心。
since it kind of hogs the core for that entire section.
是的，所以这是，没错，
Yes, yes, so this is, that's right,
所以，在 RCU 关键部分的读者，
so, readers in the rcu critical section,
在查看受保护的数据时，
while they're looking at the protected data,
它们不能上下文切换，
they can't context switch,
所以你想把这些关键部分缩短，
and so you're, you know you want to keep those critical sections short,
这是一个考虑因素。
now, and that's a consideration.
不过，它的结果是，
The way it plays out though is that,
RCU 的部署方式
the way RCU has been deployed
通常是在 Linux 中有一些代码，
is typically there will be some piece of code in Linux,
它们使用普通锁或读写锁进行保护，
that was protected with ordinary locks or read write locks,
还有一些工作量，
and somebody you know for some workloads,
我们看到锁是一个可怕的性能问题，
we'll see that lock is a terrible performance problem,
他们将替换锁临界区为 RCU 临界区，
and they're going to replace the locking critical section with an RCU critical section,
尽管有时它更复杂。
although sometimes it's more involved than that.
而且由于锁临界区已经，
And since locking critical sections were already,
把它们缩短是极其重要的，
it was extremely important to make them short,
因为当你持有锁时，
because while you hold a lock,
可能会有很多其他核心在等待那个锁，
there may be lots of other cores waiting for that lock,
所以有很大的压力来保持普通锁临界区短，
so there's a lot of pressure to keep ordinary lock critical sections short,
因为 RCU 临界区经常，
because RCU critical sections are often
是修改过的锁临界区，
sort of revised lock critical sections,
之前曾是临界区，
that used to be like critical sections,
它们往往也很短。
they tend to be short also.
这意味着，
And you know that means that,
并不总是，
you know not always,
但是通常不会有，
but usually there there's not a,
不会直接担心保持 RCU 关键部分短。
not a direct worry about keeping RCU critical sections short.
虽然这是一个限制，
Although it is a constraint,
真正的约束是你不允许持有指针通过，
the real constraint actually you're not allowed to hold pointers over,
指向 RCU 数据的指针通过上下文切换。
pointers to RCU data over context switches.
那是你不能，
And that's actually you can't,
比如，你不能读取磁盘，然后等待磁盘完成，
for example read the disks and wait for the disk wait to complete,
在持有指向 RCU 保护数据的指针时。
while while holding on a pointer, onto a pointer to RCU protected data.
所以不是很多，
So it's not quite so much,
通常出现的问题不是临界区的长度，
the the thing that usually comes up is not the length of the critical section,
[]禁止让出 CPU 。
so much as the prohibition against yielding CPU.
好的。
Okay.
让我们看看，为了更明确，
Let's see, so just kind of firm up,
我刚才说的所有的事情，
but I, all the stuff I just talked about,
这是你将看到的，
here's the kind of what you would see
一个 RCU 的简单使用。
in a simple use of RCU.
所以，这是代码，
So this is code,
你会看到用于读取列表和 RCU 保护列表，
you might see for reading a list, and rcu protected list,
而这是代码，
and this is the code,
你可能会在写入端看到，
you might see on the write side,
对于只替换第一个列表元素的特定情况的代码，
for code that just wants to a particular case of replacing the first list element,
所以在读取端，有这个，
so the read side, there is actually this,
read_lock 和 read_unlock 调用，
these read_lock and read_unlock calls,
它们几乎什么都不做，
those do almost nothing, almost nothing,
它们唯一做的就是设置一个标志，表示，
the only, the only little thing they do is set a flag, that says
或者 rcu_read_lock 设置一个标志，表示，
or rcu_read_lock sets a flag, that says,
如果发生定时器中断，请不要进行上下文切换，
if a timer interrupt happens, please don't context switch,
因为我在 RCU 临界区中间。
because I'm in the middle of rcu critical section.
所以这它说做的，
So that's all really does
设置标志禁止定时器中断上下文切换，
set a flag that prohibits timer interrupt context switches,
中断可能仍会发生，但不会切换上下文，
interrupts may still happen, but it wont context switch,
然后 read_unlock 取消标志，
and then read_unlock unset flag,
它是嵌套的 RCU 临界区的计数器。
really it's counter of nested RCU critical sections.
所以这两个函数非常快，几乎什么也不做。
So these two functions are extremely fast and do almost nothing.
然后这个循环会扫描我们的列表，
And then this loop would sort of scan down the our list,
这就是插入内存屏障的调用，
this is the call that insert the memory barrier,
所以 RCU 真的可以归结为几条指令，
so what RCU, this really boils down to just a couple of instructions,
它读取，它从内存中抓取这个指针的副本，
it just reads, it grabs a copy of this pointer from memory,
发出内存屏障，然后返回那个指针。
issues a memory barrier and then returns that pointer.
然后我们可以查看内容，
And then we can look at the content
并继续下一个列表元素。
and go on to the next list element.
所以读者很简单。
So the readers quite simple.
写者更多地参与其中，
The writers a little more involved,
写者仍然，
writers still,
RCU 并不能帮助写者避免互相干扰，
you know the RCU doesn't help writers avoid interfering with each other,
所以，写者仍然必须有某种方法
so writers still have to have some way
来确保一次只有一个写者修改列表。
of making sure only one writer modifies the list at a time.
在这种情况下，
In this case,
想象我们将使用普通的自旋锁，
I'm just imagining we're going to use ordinary spin locks,
所以写者需要锁。
so the writer requires the lock.
如果我们要替换第一个列表元素，
If we're replacing the first list element,
我们需要在一开始保存一份副本，
we need to save a copy at the beginning,
因为我们最终需要释放它，
because we're going to need to eventually free it,
所以我们保存这个老的元素的副本，
so we save this copy of the oldest element,
现在这个代码使用我刚才说过的那个技巧，
now we're this code plays that trick I talked again about,
分配一个完整的新列表元素，
allocating a complete new list element
来保存这个更新的内容。
to hold this updated content.
我们将分配一个新的列表元素，
We're gonna allocate a new list element,
我们将设置它的内容，
we're gonna set its content,
我们设置下一个指针，
we're gonna set the next pointer
设置为我们要替换的旧的第一个列表元素中的下一个指针，
to the next pointer in the old first list element as we're replacing it,
然后 rcu_assign_pointer 发出内存屏障，
and then this rcu_assign_pointer issues a memory barrier,
所以所有这些写入都发生了，
so that all these these writes happened,
然后将第一个参数所指向的指针设置为等于，
and then sets a pointer pointed to by this first argument to be equal to that,
所以，这只是发出一个内存屏障，
so basically this just issues a memory barrier
然后将 head 设置为 e 。
and then sets head equal to e.
现在我们可以释放锁了，
Now we can release the lock,
我们仍然有一个指向旧的第一个列表元素的指针，
we still have a pointer to the old first list element,
调用 synchronize_rcu 以确保每个 CPU
call synchronize_rcu to make sure every CPU
可以抓取指向旧元素的指针，
that could have grabbed a pointer to the oldest element,
在我们执行提交写入之前，让出 CPU ，
before we did the committing write has yielded the CPU
因此放弃它的指针 RCU 保护数据，
and therefore given up its pointer RCU protected data,
现在我们可以释放旧的列表元素了。
and now we could free the old list element.
有什么问题吗？
Any questions?
好的。
Alright.
关于 RCU ，需要注意的一件事是，
There RCU, one thing to note about this is that,
在读者中，
while in the reader,
虽然我们可以在这里查看循环内的列表元素，
while we're allowed to look at this list element inside the loop here,
我们不允许做的一件事是返回列表元素，
one thing we're not allowed to do is return the list element,
例如，我们使用 RCU ，
so for example we using RCU,
我们不能编写列表查找函数，
we couldn't write a lookup a list lookup function,
它返回列表元素
that returned either the list element
或指向保存在列表元素中的数据的指针，
or a pointer into data held in the list element,
比如嵌入在列表元素中的字符串。
like a string that was embedded in the list element.
因为那样我们就不再控制了，
Because then we'd be in, then we would no longer be in control,
必须是这种情况，
you know it has to be the case,
我们不会把受 RCU 保护的数据放在外面，
that we don't look at RCU protected data outside,
这个 RCU 临界区或者我们不进行上下文切换，
this RCU critical section or we don't do a context switch,
如果我们只编写一个返回列表元素的普通函数，
if we just write a generic function that returns a list element,
那么就我们所了解的调用者来说，
then for all we know the caller,
也许我们也可以让调用者遵守一些规则，
maybe we can persuade the caller to follow some rules too,
但据我们所知，调用者会进行上下文切换，
but for all we know, the caller make context switch
或者我们会遇到麻烦，
or we run into trouble
或者在返回列表元素之前调用 rcu_read_unlock ，
either we call rcu_read_unlock before returning the list element,
这是非法的，
which is illegal,
因为现在定时器中断可能会强制切换，
because now a timer interrupt could force a switch,
或者我们不调用 rcu_read_unlock 。
or we don't call rcu_read_unlock.
所以，使用 RCU 给读者带来了一些额外的约束，
So use of RCU sort of does put some additional constraints on readers,
这在以前是不存在的。
that wouldn't have existed before.
关于这一点的一个问题。
A question about that.
好的。
Yes.
所以，你是说，
So, are you saying in particular,
如果我们有某种比如读取索引 i 元素的方法，
that if we had some form of like read element at index i method,
没有办法来[组织]这件事，
that there's no way to structure this,
这样它不能返回[]元素 i 持有的值。
so that it couldn't return the value held by the [] element i.
它可以返回一个副本。
It could return a copy.
那么，如果 e->x 是一个字符串，
So what would work, you know if e->x is a string,
我们可以返回一个这个字符串的副本，
we could return a copy of this string,
这很好，
and that's fine,
会违反 RCU 的规定的是，
what would be a violation of RCU rules,
如果我们返回一个指针，指向位于内部的这个字符串，
if we return a pointer to this very string sitting inside,
将指向 e 的指针返回，是错误的。
a pointer it would be a mistake to return a pointer into somewhat into e.
如果字符串存储在列表元素内，
If the string is stored inside the list element,
我们最好不要把这个指针返回那个字符串，
we better not return this pointer that string,
因为这样，
because then, that will be,
你不能切换上下文，
you have to not context switch,
我们将指针指向 RCU 保护的数据，
we're holding a pointer into RCU protected data,
而惯例是，
and the you know the convention is
你只需要在这个关键部分使用这些数据。
you know you just use that data within this critical section.
所以，几乎可以肯定的是，这将打破惯例，
And so it would almost certainly be breaking the convention
否则这个设置会复杂得多，
or this setup would have to be much more complicated,
如果我们最终返回指向受保护数据的指针。
if we ended up returning pointers into the protected data.
谢谢。
Thank you.
我想回到性能的故事上来，
The I just want to return briefly to the performance story,
很难描述性能是什么样的，
it's, it's hard to characterize sort of what the performance is,
我的意思是，在某种意义上，
I mean in a sense,
整体性能的故事是，
the, let's see the the overall performance story is that
如果你使用 RCU ，读取会非常快，
if you use RCU, reads are extremely fast,
它们只是在执行
they just proceed at whatever,
它们没有超出普通的查看数据的开销，
they've served no overhead above the ordinary overhead of looking at that data,
所以如果你的列表有十亿个元素长，
so if your list is a billion elements long,
读取列表需要很长时间，
yeah, reading list will take a long time,
但并不是因为同步，
but it's not because synchronization,
只是因为你为读者做了很多工作。
is just because you're doing a lot of work for readers.
因此你几乎可以认为 RCU 对读者的开销为零，
So you can almost view RCU is having zero overhead for readers
例外情况很小，
and exceptions are minor,
rcu_read_lock 只需要很少的工作
rcu_read_lock, you know just a tiny amount of work
设置这个标志表示没有上下文切换，
to set this flag saying no context switches,
而 rcu_dereference 发出一个内存屏障，
and rcu_dereference issues a memory barrier,
可能会使你减慢几十个周期，
which actually might slow you down by dozens, few dozen cycles,
但是它比加锁便宜多了。
but it's much cheaper than a lock.
关于写者的性能要差得多，
The performance story for writers is much sadder,
你必须做所有的事情，
you have to do all the stuff,
你总是要用锁，
you always had to do using locks,
实际上，你必须获取并释放写者中的锁，
in fact you have to acquire and release locks in the writer,
你有一个可能非常昂贵的调用，
and you have this potentially extremely expensive call
或耗时的调用，叫做 synchronize_rcu 。
or time-consuming called synchronize_rcu.
其实你可以放弃，
In fact you can give up,
内部的 synchronize_rcu 让出 CPU ，
you know internally synchronize_rcu gives up the CPU,
所以你不一定要花时间。
so you don't doesn't spend necessarily.
但是它可能需要很多运行时间
But it may require a lot of elapsed time
等待每个其他核心进行上下文切换。
waiting for every other core to context switch.
所以根据写入的原因
So depending on the mix of reason writes
以及在读取临界区做多少工作，
and how much work was being done inside the read critical section,
性能提升大不相同，
the performance increase varies tremendously,
从速度快得多的，
from a much much faster,
如果这些关键部分很短，写入也很少，
if these critical sections were short and there's few writes too,
也可能会更慢，如果写入非常普遍。
perhaps even slower, if writes are very common.
所以，当人们将 RCU 应用于内核时，
And so when people apply RCU to kernel stuff,
你需要针对大量工作负载进行性能测试，
actually you absolutely have to do performance tests against a bunch of workloads
为了弄清楚使用 RCU 对你来说是不是优势，
in order to figure out whether using RCU is a win for you,
因为，取决于工作量。
because, so depending on the workload.
我有一个也许是离题的问题，
I have a maybe a tangential question,
但我们已经看到了，
but we've seen that,
我想当使用多个核心时，
I guess when there's multiple cores being used,
在我们通常的实现中增加了一些复杂性，
there's some added complexity to our usual implementations,
这些原子指令在某种程度上起到了拯救作用，
and it's often the these atomic instructions kind of come to the rescue
假设有一个共享的内存系统，
and that's assuming there's one shared memory system,
但我想知道，
but I wonder like
如果一台机器试图维护多个 RAM 系统，会发生什么情况，
what happens if a machine is trying to maintain like multiple RAM systems,
它是如何将这些统一起来的。
how does it unify those.
通常情况下，
The ordinary,
好的，在我们所说的水平上，
well, at a, at a at the level we're talking about,
机器有一个 RAM 系统。
the machine has one RAM system.
好的，你知道，
Okay, that's you know,
是的，对于所有那些普通的电脑来说，
yeah, it's, for all those sort of ordinary computers,
你会买多个核心，
you would buy that multiple cores,
你可以编写程序，
you can pretty much program
就像所有核心之间共享一个 RAM 系统，
as if there were just one RAM system shared among all the cores,
这就是硬件提供给你的逻辑模型，
that's the logical model the hardware provides you,
在物理层面上，并不经常是这样的。
at physical levels not like that often.
有很多机器都有这种物理布局，
There's plenty of machines out there that have this physical arrangement,
我们有一个 CPU 芯片，
we have a CPU chip,
这是一个 CPU 芯片，
so here's one CPU chip,
可能上面有很多核心。
maybe with lots of cores on it, right.
你得到的 CPU 芯片，
And you get CPU chips with,
我不知道现在有多少核，比如说 32 个核，
I don't know how many cores these days, say 32 cores,
假设你想构建一台 64 核计算机，
let's say you want to build a 64 core machine,
你可以只买 32 核芯片，
you can only buy 32 core chips,
你可以做一块有两个芯片插槽的电路板，
well you can make a board that has two sockets for chips on it,
所以现在我们有两个芯片，
so now we have two chips,
获得内存的最快方式是
the fastest way to get at memory is
使内存或多或少尽可能直接连接到 CPU 芯片，
to have the memory more or less as directly attached to the CPU chip as possible,
所以你要做的就是在这里放一组非常粗的电线，
so what you would do is you'd have like a very fat set of wires here,
在芯片旁边是一大堆 RAM 。
to right next to the chip a bunch of RAM.
所以它可以直接访问，
So it has direct access
当然这个芯片也需要自己的 RAM 。
and of course this chips going to want its own RAM also, right.
所以这是，
So so this is,
我画了一幅你会看到的图片，
I'm just drawing a picture of what you would see,
如果你打开一台有两个处理器芯片和 RAM 的个人计算机。
if you opened up a PC with two processor chips and RAM.
但是现在我们面临一个问题，
But now we're faced with a problem,
如果这个芯片上的一个软件，
what happens if a software over on this chip,
使用实际存储在这个 RAM 中的内存位置。
uses a memory location it's actually stored in this RAM.
所以，实际上这两个芯片之间也存在互连，
So in fact there's also a interconnect between these two chips,
通常是极快的互连，
generally an extremely fast interconnect,
例如每秒千兆字节，
like gigabytes per second,
而且芯片足够智能，
and the chips are smart enough
可以知道某些物理内存位置在这组 RAM 中，
to know that certain physical memory locations are in this bank of RAM,
而其他物理位置，物理内存地址在这一组 RAM 中，
and other physical locations, physical memory addresses are in this bank of RAM,
这里的软件使用物理地址通过这个，
of software here uses a physical address is over this one,
芯片足够聪明来发送消息，
the chip is clever enough to send a message,
基本上通过小网络，
basically little network,
通过这个芯片发送消息，
send a message over this chip,
我需要读取一些 RAM ，请这样做，
look I need to read some RAM, please do it,
去读取它的 RAM 并返回结果。
go read its RAM and send the result back.
你可以买四个芯片阵列，
You can buy four chip arrangements
使用这样复杂的互连，
with the same thing with a complex interconnect like this,
这需要进行大量的工程，
there's a huge amount of engineering going on
为了映射简单的共享 RAM 模型，
in order to map the straightforward shared RAM model
在现实生活中建立什么样的高性能是可行的，
onto what sort of feasible to build with high performance in real life,
并适用于二维或三维空间。
and fit in two or three dimensions.
这回答了你的问题吗？
Is that answer your question?
是的，这提供了很多背景信息，谢谢。
Yeah, yeah, that provides a lot of context, thank you.
好的。
Okay.
好的，对实际技术，有什么问题吗？
Yeah, any questions on the actual technique?
好的，那么，
Alright so,
我相信你已经意识到 RCU 并不是普遍适用的，
as, I'm sure you've got the sense of RCU is not universally applicable,
这里没有，
there's not,
你不能把每一种使用自旋锁，
you can't just take every situation in which using spin locks
获得糟糕并行性能的情况，
and getting bad parallel performance
并将其转换为 RCU 以获得更好的性能，
and convert it to RCU and get better performance,
主要原因是，它完全无助于写入，速度更慢了。
because, the main reason it completely doesn't help writes makes them slower.
只是获得性能，
You know really only helps performance,
只有在读取数量大大超过写入的情况下。
if if the reads outnumber the writes considerably.
它有这样的限制，
It has this restriction that
你不能在睡眠期间持有指针来保护数据，
you can't hold pointers to protect the data across sleep,
这会让某种代码变得相当笨拙，
which just makes some kind of code quite awkward,
如果你真的需要睡觉，
if you actually need to sleep,
那么你可能需要重新查找它是什么。
you may then need to re-lookup whatever it is.
所以在睡眠结束后再做一次 RCU 临界区，
So you know to do another RCU critical section after the sleep completes,
为了再次查找，
in order to look again
对你原来查看的这个数据，
for, for the data that you originally were looking at,
假设它还存在，
assuming it's still even exists,
所以这会让代码变得更复杂。
so it just makes code a bit more complicated.
数据结构，应用它的最直接方式是，
The data structures, the most straightforward way to apply it is,
那个数据结构具有一个结构，
the data structures that have a structure,
服从于用于更新的单次提交写入，
that's amenable to single committing writes for updates,
你不能在原地修改东西，你必须替换东西，
you can't modify things in place, so you have to replace stuff,
比如列表和树，
so you know list and trees,
但不是更复杂的数据结构，
but not more complex data structures,
论文提到了一些更复杂的方式，比如顺序锁，
the paper mentioned some more complicated ways like sequence locks,
能够在适当的位置更新东西，
to be able to update stuff in place,
尽管读者没有使用锁，
despite readers that aren't using locks,
但它们变得越来越复杂，
but they are getting more complicated
它们实际提高性能的情况受到更多限制。
and the situations under which they actually improve performance are more restricted.
另一个微妙的问题是，
Another subtle problem is that,
读者可以看到旧的数据，
readers can see stale data,
对于它们可以看到旧的数据的时间没有任何明显的限制，
without any obvious bound on how long they can see stale data for,
因为如果某个读者获得指向 RCU 保护对象的指针，
because if some reader gets a pointer to a RCU protected object,
正好在写者替换它之前，
just before a writer replaces it,
读者可能会在相当长的一段时间内仍然持有该数据，
the reader may still hold on to that data for quite a long time,
至少在现代计算机指令的规模上，
at least on the scale of modern computer instructions,
很多时候，这是无关紧要的，
and a lot of the time, this turns out not to matter much,
但是论文提到了一些其实我不太理解的情况，
but the paper mentioned some situations which I actually don't really understand,
人们期望写入在写入完成后立即生效，
in which people expect writes to actually take effect after the write completes,
因此，读者看到旧的数据有点令人惊讶。
and therefore, which readers see stale data is a bit of a surprise.
你也可能，
You may also,
作为一个单独的主题，
as a separate topic,
你可能还想知道如果写入大量数据会发生什么情况，
wonder what happens if you have write heavy data,
就像 RCU 完全是关于读取大量数据，
like RCU is all about read heavy data,
但这只是你可能关心的许多情况之一，
but that's just one of many situations you might care about,
对于获得并行性能，
for getting parallel performance,
他们还关心写入大量数据。
they also care about write heavy data.
实际上，在一些写入大量数据的极端情况下，
Actually, in the extremes, in some extreme cases of write heavy data,
你可以做得很好，
you can do quite well,
据我所知，没有一种技术可以写入大量数据，
there's no technique I know of for write heavy data,
像 RCU 一样普遍适用，
that's quite as universally applicable as RCU,
但仍然有一些想法可以处理大部分是写入的数据。
but there are still ideas for coping with data that's mostly written.
最强大的想法是重组你的数据，
The most powerful idea is to restructure your data,
重组数据结构，使其不共享，
restructure the data structure, so it's not shared,
有时候你可以做到，
and sometimes you can do,
有时候分享是完全[无端的]，
that sometimes the sharing is just completely gratuitous,
一旦你意识到这是个问题，你就可以把它处理掉。
and you can get rid of it once you realize it's a problem.
但通常情况也是这样，
But it's also often the case,
当你有时确实需要共享数据，
that the that while you do sometimes need to have shared data,
通常情况下不需要不同的核心写入相同的数据，
that the common case doesn't require different cores to write the same data,
即使他们需要大量写入一些数据。
even though they need to write some of the data a lot.
你实际上已经在实验里看到了这一点，
And you've actually seen that in the labs,
在锁实验里，
in the locking lab,
在实验的 kalloc 部分，
in the kalloc part of the lab,
您重构了空闲列表，
you restructured the free list,
以便每个核心都有一个专用的空闲列表，
so that each core has a dedicated free list,
从而将写入繁重的数据结构空闲列表
thus converting a write heavy data structure the free list
转换为每个核心的半私有的数据结构，
into one that was a semi-private per core,
所以大多数时候，核心只需要，
so most of the times cores just have to,
它们不会与其他核心冲突，
they don't conflict with other cores,
因为它们有自己的私有空闲列表，
because they have their own private free list
你唯一需要查看其他空闲列表的时间是，
and the only time you have to look at other free lists is,
如果你的空闲列表用完了。
if your free list runs out.
这里有很多例子，
There are actually many examples
使用这种方法处理在内核中的大量写入数据，
of this way of dealing with write heavy data in the kernel,
比如分配器 Linux 是这样的，
thinking the allocator Linux is like this,
Linux 的调度列表。
Linux's scheduling lists.
每个核心都有一组单独的线程，
There's a separate set of threads for each core,
调度程序大部分时间都在查看，
that the scheduler looks at most of the time,
并且内核只需查看彼此的调度列表，
and cores only have to look at each others scheduling list,
它们没有工作可做了。
they run out of work to do.
另一个例子是统计计数器，
Another example is statistics counters,
如果你在计算什么，
if you're counting something
计数变化很大，但很少读取，
and the counts go change a lot, but they're rarely read,
计数是由写而不是读主导，
that is the counts are truly dominated by writes not reads,
你可以重组计数，
you can restructure your counter,
使每个核心都有单独的计数，
so that each core has a separate counter,
所以，每个核心只需要修改自己的计数，
and so each core just modifies its own counter,
当它需要修改计数时
when it needs to change the count,
如果你想读点什么东西，
and if you want to read something,
然后你必须出去，
then you have to go out
加锁并读取每个核心的所有计数，
and lock and read all the per core counters,
所以这是一种写入非常快的技术。
so that's a technique to make writes very fast.
因为写者只修改本地每个核心的计数，
Because the writers just modify the local per core counter,
但现在的读取非常慢，
but the reads are now very slow,
但是如果你的计数写入为主，
and you know, but if your counters are write heavy
通常计数都是那样的。
as just the counters often are.
这可能是一个巨大的胜利，
That could be a big win
将工作转移到读者上。
shifting the work now to the reads.
所以关键是有一些技巧，
So the point is there are techniques,
尽管我们没有谈论太多，
even though we didn't talk about that much,
有时也有一些技术可以帮助写入密集型工作负载。
there are also sometimes techniques that help for write intensive workloads.
为了完成 RCU ，
To wrap up the RCU,
我们在论文中读到的东西
the stuff we read about in the paper
实际上是 Linux 的一个巨大的成功故事，
is actually a giant success story for Linux,
在 Linux 上到处都用来获取各种不同的数据，
is used all over Linux to get at all kinds of different data,
因为事实证明，
because it just turns out that
读取为主的，读取密集型数据，是非常常见的，
read and read mostly data read intensive data, it's extremely common,
比如，高速缓存的文件块，大多是读取的，
like cached file blocks, for example are mostly read,
所以，一种只加快读取速度的技术是一种非常广泛的应用。
so a technique that speeds up only reads is a really very widely applicable.
而且 RCU 特别有魔力，
And RCU is particularly magic,
还有很多其他有趣的并发技术，同步技术，
there's lots of other interesting concurrency techniques, synchronization techniques,
RCU 是神奇的，
RCU is magic,
因为它完全消除了对读者的加锁和写入，
because it completely eliminates locking and writing for the readers,
所以这是一个很大的突破，
so it's just a big breakthrough
与读写锁相比，
compared to things like read write locks,
这些是以前最先进的。
which were the previous state of the art.
而真正让它发挥作用的关键思想是，
And the key idea that really makes it work is the,
垃圾收集，
sort of garbage collection,
比如推迟冻结，他们称为宽限期，
like deferring a freeze for what they call the grace period,
保证所有读者都完成使用数据之前，
until all the readers are guaranteed to be finished using the data,
所以可以像同步技术一样，
so you can all as well as the synchronization technique,
把它看作是一个非常，
it's actually fair to view it as a very much,
作为一种特殊的垃圾收集技术。
so as a kind of a specialized garbage collection technique.
这些是我要说的，
And that is all I have to say,
所以我很乐意回答大家的问题。
so I'm happy to take questions.
哦，抱歉，你能给解释一下读者的旧数据吗，
Oh, sorry, can you explain the stale data for readers,
所以我不明白为什么会发生这种事，
so I don't understand why how that can happen,
因为你在读你的关键区域，
because you you're reading your critical section,
而且，你只是得到当时的任何数据，
and, you just get whatever data is there at that point,
然后你只是。
and then you just.
这通常不是问题，
It actually usually is not a problem,
但是为什么会出现这样的情况，
but the reason why ever might come up,
通常情况下，如果你有代码比如 x 等于 1 ，
well ordinarily, you know if you have code that says x equals 1,
然后你打印 done ，
and then you know print done,
天哪，这是相当令人惊讶的，
gosh, it's pretty surprising,
如果在这一点之后，
if after this point,
有人读取数据，看到在你将其设置为 1 的值。
someone reading the data, sees that value before you set it to 1.
这可能有点意外，对吧。
Right, that's a maybe a bit of a surprise, right.
有一种感觉是 RCU 允许这样的事情发生，
Well, there's a sense in which RCU allows that to happen, right,
我们要讨论的问题是，
if this is really what we're really talking about is,
list_replace 查找包含 1 的元素，
you know list_replace whatever you know find the element that has 1
然后把它改成 2 ，
and change it to 2,
通过使用 RCU ，
with using RCU, right,
在那之后，我们打印，我们完成了，
after that finishes, we print, oh yeah we're done,
如果有读者正在查看列表，
if there's some reader that was looking at the list, right,
他们刚好访问了那个列表元素，
they may have you know just gotten to the list element,
包含 1 的，我们替换为 2 的，
that held one, that we replaced with 2,
然后很长一段时间，
and then a good deal longer,
然后它们读取列表元素，
you know, and then they do the actual read of the list element,
它们查看，
you know they look at
在我们完成后，列表元素中的内容，
whatever the content is in the list element after we've done this,
他们读取列表元素，
you know they're reading the list element,
只是在稍后的这一点上，
only at this point later in time,
他们看到了旧的值，
and they see the old value,
所以如果你没有做好准备，
so if you're not prepared for this,
现在这有点奇怪了。
this is a little bit odd now.
我的意思是他们甚至可能做了内存屏障，
I mean they, they may even do a memory barrier right,
我是说这不是内存屏障问题，只是。
I mean it's not a memory barrier issue, is just like.
事实上，在大多数情况下，这都无关紧要。
And indeed, most of the time, it doesn't matter.
我明白了，所以这是当替换非常接近的时候，
I see, so this is when this replace is very close,
所以他们读取在替换前就开始了，
so like they read somehow like starts before the replace,
但需要一段时间，而且。
but it is takes a while, and.
是的，如果读者比写者慢。
Yes, yeah, the reader if the reader is slower than the writer or something.
现在，我觉得这基本上不重要，
Now, you know, I think this mostly doesn't matter,
因为最终读者和写者是同时行动的，
because after all, the reader and the writer were acting concurrently
两件事同时发生，
and you know two things happen concurrently,
通常，你怎么也想不到，
usually you, you would never have imagined
你会得到很多关于确认顺序的保证，
that you could have been guaranteed much about the exact order,
如果同时调用这两个操作。
if the two operations were invoked concurrently.
这篇论文声称，
The paper claims,
我是说，作为这篇论文中的一个例子，
I mean, the paper as an example in which they said it matters,
它造成了一个真正的问题，
it turned out to cause a real problem,
虽然我不明白为什么会这样。
although I don't really understand why that was.
我明白了，有道理，
I see, this makes sense,
我的另一个问题是，
and my other question was,
它之所以被称为 RCU ，是因为想法一，是吗？
it's called a RCU because of idea one, is that right.
读取复制更新，是的，
Read copy update, yes,
我相信是因为想法一，
I believe it's because of idea one,
也就是说，不是原地修改东西，
that is that instead of modifying things in place,
你复制了一份，
you make a copy and you sort of copy
而不是真的东西。
not the that's the real thing.
好的，很有道理，非常感谢。
Right, this makes sense, thank you so much.
好的。
Yes.
所以在课程开始的时候，
So at the beginning of lecture
或者接近开始时我们讨论了 n 平方[运行时]，
or towards the beginning we talked about the of n squared [runtime]
对于缓存一致性协议，
for the cache coherence protocols,
为了更新读写锁，
for updating the read write locks,
这不也是自旋锁的问题吗。
isn't this also a problem with spin locks, where.
是的，好的，
Yeah, okay,
那么原因是什么，
so so what is the reason,
为什么我们没有讨论这一方面。
why we didn't discuss that aspect.
为什么我们没有。
Why we didn't.
是啊，或者，
Yeah or like,
有没有理由说它仍然存在，
is there a reason that that still exists
或者自旋锁是怎么解决这个问题的。
or are like what do spin locks do to address that.
好的。
Okay.
锁非常昂贵，
Locks are hideously expensive,
如果有标准的自旋锁，像 xv6 那样，
if there are standard spin locks, like xv6 has,
如果锁不是特别争用，是非常快的，
are extremely fast, if the lock is not particularly contended,
是非常慢的，如果多个核心试图同时获得相同的锁。
and terribly slow, if lots of cores try to get the same lock at the same time.
好的，这是让生活变得有趣的一件事，
Okay, yeah, this is one of the things that makes life interesting,
你知道，有一些，
and you know there's,
是的，我的意思是，有一些锁，它的伸缩性更好，
yeah, I mean there's there's locks that are a better scaling,
但更糟糕的是，
but worse,
它们具有较好的高负载性能，
they have better high load performance,
但较差的低负载性能。
but worse low load performance.
好的，谢谢。
Okay,thanks.
但我不关心有没有锁，
But I'm not aware of a lock that is,
不管怎么说，这件事很难做对，
anyway, it's hard it's hard to get this stuff, right,
在这些机器上很难获得好的性能。
it's hard to get good performance on these machines.
还有其他问题吗？
Other questions?
这可能是无关的，
This might be unrelated,
但在多个不同的系统之间会有锁相关的游戏吗，
but can there ever be a lock of games between multiple different systems,
比如不仅局限于一个系统，
like like not just contained to one system,
比如可能是多台服务器。
maybe like multiple servers perhaps.
这里绝对有分布式系统，
There are absolutely distributed systems,
其中有一种锁，
in which there's a sort of locking,
其中的统一锁跨越多台机器，
in which that sort of universal locks spans multiple machines,
当分布式数据库中出现时，
when places comes up in distributed databases
你会在多个服务器上显示你的数据，
where the data you've met you display your data over multiple servers,
但是如果你有一个事务，
but if you have a transaction,
使用不同服务器上的不同数据，
that uses data this you know different pieces of data on different servers,
你需要[收集]锁。
you need gonna need to [collect] locks.
它们在，
They were in,
你需要从多个服务器上收集锁。
you need to basically collect locks from multiple servers.
另一个出现的地方，
Another place that comes up,
虽然已经有很多系统
although there's been a number of systems
试图在独立的机器上模拟共享内存，
that are essentially tried to mimic shared memory across independent machines,
对于这些机器，
with the machines,
如果我使用机器中的一些内存，
if I use some memory that's in your machine,
然后有一些基础设施
then there's some infrastructure stuff
会导致我的计算机与你的计算机交互，
that causes my machine to talk to your machine
并申请内存，
and ask for the memory,
然后游戏通常是
and you know then the game is usually
在一群工作站上运行现有的并行程序，
to run existing parallel programs on a cluster of workstations
而不是在一台大型的多核机器上，
instead of on a big multi-core machine,
希望这会便宜一点。
hoping this is going to be cheaper.
在那里，自旋锁有一些事情要做，
And you know something needs to be done about spin locks there
或者你要用的任何锁。
or whatever locking you're going to use.
人们发明了各种方法
And so people have invented various ways
来使锁在这种情况下工作得很好。
to make the locking work out well in that case too.
你使用的技术通常和这个不太一样，
You using techniques that are not often not quite the same as this,
虽然避免压力，
although the pressure to avoid,
避免成本的压力在那块更高。
the pressure to avoid costs is even higher in that piece.
还要别的吗？
Anything else?
谢谢。
Thank you.
不用谢。
You're welcome.